<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Catalogus Protestantium: or, the Protestants kalender Containing a suruiew of the Protestants religion long before Luthers dayes, euen to the time of the Apostles, and in the primitiue Church. By George Web D. of Diuinity, and preacher of the Word of God at the Bathe.</title>
            <author>Webbe, George, 1581-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 210 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68865</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25161</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119580</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854787</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854787</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20231</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68865)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20231)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1436:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Catalogus Protestantium: or, the Protestants kalender Containing a suruiew of the Protestants religion long before Luthers dayes, euen to the time of the Apostles, and in the primitiue Church. By George Web D. of Diuinity, and preacher of the Word of God at the Bathe.</title>
                  <author>Webbe, George, 1581-1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 26, 37-64 p., 65-72 leaves, 63-97, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Miles Flesher] for Nathanael Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reissue, with added general title page in red and black, of the edition with title page printed in black only and lacking author's name. Variant: original title page cancelled.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The Protestants kalender.</note>
                  <note>The epistle by John Gee, [par.]² , was printed as N2.3.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Central Library (Bristol, Eng.).</note>
                  <note>Added title page mutilated; lacking all after K4. Title pages and pages 72-end from the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library copy spliced at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestantism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20231:49"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20231:49"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Catalogus Proteſtantium<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Or,</hi> THE PROTESTANTS KALENDER.</p>
            <p>Containing A SVRVIEW OF THE PROTESTANTS Religion long before <hi>Luthers</hi> dayes, euen to the time of the Apoſtles, and in the Primitiue Church.</p>
            <p>BY GEORGE WEB D. of Diuinity, and Preacher of the Word of God at the Bathe.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>Nathanael Butter.</hi> 1624.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20231:1"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:20231:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20231:2"/>
            <head>An Epiſtle written by a Friend to the Author in his abſence.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian, and diſcreet Reader, It were a great defrauding the Store-houſe of Religion, to conceale that for any priuate reſpect, which concernes a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like benefit.<note place="margin">Aug. Confeſſ. lib. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Veritatem cela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, eſt aurum ſepelire:</hi> To conceale the Truth (ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) is to bury Gold; and to ſmother any ancient Sacred te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of Antiquitie, were to hide that treaſurie in the bowels of the earth, which is the ineſtimable Dowre of Gods Church. Now of all truth, and of all teſtimonies deriued from the roote and record of Antiquitie, none ought to bee more ſought after then the retayned puritie of Apoſtolique Doctrine, reſplendent in all Ages ſince our Sauiours plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, euen in the gloomie and darke dayes before <hi>Luther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Prieſts and Jeſuites for their vnpleaſant
<pb facs="tcp:20231:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20231:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20231:4"/> clamorous, and obſtriperous ſound, not vnfitly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling Frogs and Locuſts, haue of late dayes beene croaking and throtling out this harſh note and noyſe to euery Proteſtant paſſenger, <hi>Where was your Church before LVTHER?</hi> Thinking belike ſo to choake vs with this Queſtion, as that not giuing vs leaue to fetch breath, wee ſhould not poſſibly bee able to deriue our Religion from any ancienter Author. But alaſſe poore Romaniſts! Though it would ſerue our turnes to anſwer with <hi>Ignatius</hi> the Martyr,<note place="margin">Jgnat. Epiſt. ad Philad.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>IESVS CHRIST</hi> is my Antiquitie. Yet it ſhall appeare vnto you that Almightie <hi>GOD,</hi> hath not left his Truth (howſoeuer oppoſed by your impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous rabble and malice) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to bee without ſufficient witneſſe in all Ages, as may appeare by the Writings of many Chriſtian Antiquaries, who haue deliuered the Lampe of knowledge and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to vs, and for the future benefit of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian World, is now more plainly expreſſed by the Learned labour of this Reuerend Diuine, out of whoſe large field of obſeruation and Reading, hee hath affoorded you ſo faire a Kalender and plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Catalogue of Names, as may ſuffice to point out a Proteſtant ſucceſſiue Church from Age to Age. Yea it is hereby eaſily ſeene, that the Church
<pb facs="tcp:20231:4"/> of <hi>England,</hi> hath not wanted multitudes of well diſpoſed hearts at all times; howſoeuer the publike authority at ſome time lacked, to maintayne the open Preaching of the Goſpell. As for the worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this worke, worthyeſt theſe times, let the goodneſſe of God bee duely glorified, and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors paines-taking therein acknowledged: ſo ſhall the doubtfull bee better informed, the weake con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, and many a ſoule benefited.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy welwiller in Chriſt, IOHN GEE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20231:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20231:5"/>
            <head>THE PROTESTANTS KALENDER:</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Deuteronomie 32.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Remember the daies of old, conſider the yeares of many generations, aske thy father, and he will ſhew thee: thine elders, and they will tell thee.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the <hi>Athenians</hi> had conſulted the oracle of <hi>Apollo Pythius</hi> what Religion it were fitteſt for them to profeſſe:<note place="margin">Xenophon</note> They receiued this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That they ſhould follow the religion of their Anceſtors: and when they againe had replyed, that their anceſtors had often changed their religion, and therefore they knew not in ſuch an often alteration which to follow, the Oracle reſolued them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>M.</hi> Tull. Cleere, de natura Deo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> 
               <hi>Illud optimum quod &amp; pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum,</hi> That is beſt which was at the firſt. The maine controuerſie at this day in the world is about religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in the great variety whereof, among Iewes, Pagans, Turks, and Infidels, yea among thoſe who call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues by the name of Chriſtians, many weake and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable ſoules ſtand as in a maze, and know not where to ſettle themſelues.<note place="margin">Auguſtine. Arnobius.</note> Now albeit (as both <hi>Auguſtin</hi> &amp; <hi>Arnobius</hi> well obſerue) Religion is not ſo much to be weighed by time as by truth, neither is it ſo much to be enquired after whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it began, as how it is to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed; yea it cannot be denied (which <hi>Tertullian</hi> doth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20231:6"/> auerre) that the Antiquity of Religion doth much ſerue to teſtifie the verity therof,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>enul.</note> and the longer time it hath had of continuance, the more it claimes our obſeruance, and ties vs to obedience. The Heathen <hi>Heſiod</hi> could ſay <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> The old law is beſt,<note place="margin">Heſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od.</note> And the beſt and moſt diuine of all the Philoſophers <hi>Plato,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plato.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> The Ancients are beſt, as comming neereſt vnto God: And it is a rule among Lawyers, <hi>Qui prior eſt tempore, potior eſt iure,</hi> He that is firſt in time hath the chiefeſt right;<note place="margin">Iob, 8.8, 9, 10.</note> hence is it that <hi>Bildad</hi> thus aduiſeth <hi>Iob,</hi> 8.8, 9. <hi>Inquire I pray thee of the former age, prepare thy ſelfe to the ſearch of their fathers, for we are but of yeſterday, and know nothing, becauſe our daies vpon the earth are but a ſhadow: ſhall not they teach thee, and tell thee?</hi> And <hi>Iere.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, Stand ye in the waies, and ſee, aske for the old paths, where is the good way, and walke therein, and ye ſhall find reſt for your ſoules.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32.7.</note> And in the ſong of <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 32.7. <hi>Remember the daies of old, conſider the yeares of many generations, aske thy father and he ſhall ſhew thee, thine elders and they will tel thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This tryall of our <hi>Religion</hi> by <hi>Antiquity</hi> I vndertake in the following diſcourſe, not ſo much againſt the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt</hi> who ſhaketh off all religion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip Mornie</hi> treatiſe of the truth of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> as if there were no vſe of it at all: for I could ſhew him that religion had a being ſo ſoone as there was any being; and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men were tyed to any obedience by humane Lawes, before they furniſhed their mindes with any Arts, before they wore cloathes on their backs, <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> was in vſe. Neither againſt the Turks &amp; Pagans, for I could ſhew them the Antiquity of true <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> long before their new deuiſed ſuperſtitions,<note place="margin">Clem. Ale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> &amp; that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20231:6"/> whatſoeuer light they had of <hi>Religion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Campian. Greg. <hi>de Vale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Fiſher in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with D. <hi>Feally.</hi>
               </note> whatſoeuer ſhew of goodnes they haue in their ſeuerall <hi>Religions,</hi> they haue borrowed, or rather (like theeues) filched it from hence: but my tryall &amp; Apologie is framed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Papiſts, who exclaime againſt vs as <hi>Noue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts,</hi> and condemne our religion as a late vpſtart, chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging vs to ſhew where our Church, where our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion was in former times? which challenge of theirs howſoeuer it hath been anſwered to the full at diuers times, by diuers learned Worthies in our Church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>D.</hi> Field <hi>of the Church. D.</hi> Morton. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thol.</hi> Ap. <hi>D.</hi> Vſher de con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tin. flat. eccleſ. <hi>Archb. of</hi> Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terb. <hi>treatiſe of perpet. viſib. of the Church.</hi> Patrick Symſon. Richard Bernard Auguſt. de Trin. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>3. &amp;</hi> de mendac. c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> &amp; of late hath receiued a full ſatisfaction (if any thing will ſatisfie ſuch vnquiet ſpirits) by the moſt Reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Father &amp; higheſt Prelate in our Church, ſo that the moſt part of the bookes which of late come from the preſſe, are written of this ſubiect; yet I hope this mine after gleaning ſhall neither ſeeme preſumptuous nor ſuperfluous: It is the counſell &amp; aduiſe of S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> that at ſuch times, and vpon ſuch occaſions as theſe are, <hi>al men ſhould write, that haue any faculty in writing, albeit it be but the ſame things in other words, that all ſorts of people among many books might light vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome, and the enemie in all places might find ſome to encounter him: For</hi> Zions <hi>ſake I could not hold my peace, and for</hi> Ieruſalems <hi>ſake I could not reſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 62, 1.</note> 
               <hi>vntill the righteouſneſſe thereof goe forth as brightneſſe, and the ſaluation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as a lampe that burneth.</hi> And if any ſhall demand of me, as <hi>Ioab</hi> did of <hi>Ahimaaz,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 18.12, 13.</note> why I would be ſo deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to run this way after ſo many better-footed <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhies,</hi> mine Apology is, yet let me runne after them, though it be like <hi>Aſcanius, Non paſsibus aequis,</hi> althogh the matter bee the ſame, or much more mean, my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod peraduenture may be more plaine.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:20231:7"/>
            <p>For in this controuerſie betweene vs and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the Antiquity of both our Churches, I follow the tract preſcribed by <hi>Moſes.</hi> 1, Looking backe into the dayes of old, and the yeares of many generations. 2, Making inquiry of our fathers, and our elders, that they may ſhew and tell vs, whether Church, whether Religion is the ancienteſt.</p>
            <p>And I begin firſt with the firſt. The triall of the truth hereof by the antiquitie of time, becauſe the Papiſts now adaies principally inſiſt vpon this point. <hi>The Church of God</hi> (ſay they) <hi>conſiſteth not of a few people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bell. de eccleſ. lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi> Gregor. de Valen. tom. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>142.</hi> Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter. Enchir. c. <hi>2.</hi> Rhemiſt. in Act. <hi>11.24.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>but of many; it is not hidden or obſcure, but conſpicuous; the company thereof perpetually holdeth a viſible ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Paſtors and people, as ſenſibly as any other ſociety of men, ſo that any time, one may point with his finger and ſay, this is the Church.</hi> But the Proteſtants Church cannot ſhew this; <hi>ergo</hi> it is no true Chuch. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that tenent of theirs about the perpetuall viſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Church (in that ſenſe as they take it) how infirme it is I refer the reader to the learned Treatiſes of the moſt reuerend and iudicious Diuines of our Church,<note place="margin">Archbiſhop of <hi>Cant.</hi> in his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the viſibl: of the Church. D. <hi>Field</hi> of the Church. D. <hi>Whites</hi> way to the true Church.</note> who haue purpoſely written of that Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I rather bend my ſelfe to refute their Minor propoſition, wherein they deny that we of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Church can ſhew any ſuch ſucceſſion or viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of our Church and Religion in former times. And that ſo much the rather becauſe <hi>Gregory</hi> of <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenza</hi> peremptorily maintaineth,<note place="margin">Greg. de Valen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>142.</hi>
               </note> that this is a point which puſſeleth vs extreamly, &amp; that we are not able to ſhew any company of people, which in times paſt was knowne in the world to hold that forme of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine &amp; religion which we haue brought in: wherein
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20231:7"/> albeit (as their owne <hi>Bellarmine</hi> confeſſeth) <hi>It is not required to the vniuerſality of the Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellar. not. eccl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity there be at all times in euery Country ſome beleeuers, it ſufficeth if there be ſucceſsiuely: whence</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>it followeth that if only one Prouince did retaine the true faith, yet ſhould it truly and properly be called the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, as long as it might be ſhewed that it were the ſame which it was at other times in other places of the world:</hi> yet (ſuch hath been the ſingular mercy of God to his Church in the manifeſtation thereof) that we are able to ſhew that there hath beene no place in Chriſtendome, but there haue been ſome of our reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion therein, as not only our own experience,<note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>z. ſign eccleſ. lib. <hi>19.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> Bellar. de Rom. Pont. lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> but our aduerſaries owne reports beare witneſſe, when they complaine how our hereſie (ſo hereticks ſtyle it) hath poſſeſſed many and large Prouinces. To make this the better manifeſt, I ſhall in the enſuing diſcourſe ſet downe as in a Table, a particular Catalogue in what places, at what times, by what perſons our Religion hath been profeſſed and maintained in former ages. For an introduction whereunto, let vs firſt conſider what our Aduerſaries do except againſt vs.</p>
            <p>As the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſometimes ſpake vnto our Sauiour, <hi>Thou art not yet fifty yeares old,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 8.57.</note> 
               <hi>and haſt thou ſeene</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham? ſo the Papiſts ſay to vs,<note place="margin">Rhem. annot. in Epheſ <hi>4.</hi> v. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> Your Religion is not yet an hundred yeeres old, and can ſuch a Religion be good? And as the Gentiles ſometimes vpbraided the Primitiue Chriſtians,<note place="margin">Prudent periph. hymn. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nunc dogma nobis Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> naſcitur poſt euolutos mille demu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſules,</hi> Now after we know not how many thouſand Conſul-times, the Chriſtian Religion forſooth is ſtart vp. So the Papiſts obiect againſt vs: now at the laſt, after ſo many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb facs="tcp:20231:8"/> yeares,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Campian.</hi> Bell. de eccleſ. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> after ſo many hundred Popes, after ſo long continuance of the faith and doctrine of the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> without any alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or oppoſition; The Proteſtant Religion is ſprung vp, the firſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereof being <hi>Martin Luther</hi> an Apoſtate Frier &amp;c.<note place="margin">Popiſh diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning faith. <hi>p.</hi> 57.</note> The Proteſtant Religion (ſaith the Ieſuit) was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer heard of before <hi>Martin Luther</hi> ſet it abroach: and a late popiſh Doctor bluſheth not to vtter, that it is moſt manifeſt that all in <hi>England</hi> were Papiſts with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception from the firſt chriſtning thereof vntill about the latter end of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight.<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ide Archb. of Cant. de viſib. eccleſ. p. <hi>74.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>What, was our Religion neuer heard of before <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> ſet it abroach? were all in <hi>England</hi> Papiſts, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one without exception in that religion, from the firſt time that it was Chriſtian, till <hi>Henry</hi> the eight brought in an Innouation? Let vs try the honeſty of theſe Popiſh Doctors: and by a view of this, try how in other things we may truſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on their words, let vs (according to the counſell of <hi>Moſes</hi> the man of God) looke to the dayes of old, and the yeares of many generations, let vs ſearch the records of time, and beginning with <hi>Luther,</hi> looke backward vnto the former times, to the yeares of many generations that were before him, and if we do not find the footſteps of our Religion in thoſe ancienter dayes, let the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts be credited, and our mouthes ſtopped.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20231:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Martin Luther</hi> was borne at <hi>Iſleben</hi> in <hi>Saxony,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Maſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> lib. <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Caſp pencer. l. <hi>5.</hi> Abbat Vſperg. Iob. Sleidun. Martyrol. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glic. p. <hi>771, 772.</hi>
               </note> Anno Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini 1483. Hee was brought vp in the Vniuerſitie firſt of <hi>Magdeburg,</hi> then of <hi>Erford,</hi> and afterwards at <hi>Wittenburgh,</hi> where at the age of 29 he commenced Doctor. At the firſt he was a Monke of the <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Order, and he beganne to diſtaſt Popiſh religion about the yeare of our Lord 1516, by occaſion of his looking into, firſt, the Pardons and Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences which Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth ſet to ſale in <hi>Germany</hi> by Frier <hi>Tecellius,</hi> and afterwards by prying into other ſtuffe of Popiſh ſuperſtitions: ſo that the time of his ſeparation from the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> muſt be reckoned to be about the yere of our Lord, 1516, or 1517.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight ſhoke off the Popiſh yoake about the 25 yeare of his reigne,<note place="margin">Chronic. Ang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ic. in vita Hen. <hi>8.</hi> Statut. ann. regni <hi>25. Acts and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</hi> p. <hi>96<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>viz. Anno Domini</hi> 1534 Before which time he wrote againſt <hi>Luther,</hi> and was an earneſt defender of the Papacy.</p>
            <p>Before either of theſe two times, and whilſt both <hi>Henry</hi> the eight and <hi>Luther</hi> were Papiſts, wee can produce profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of our Religion betweene the yeare of our Lord 1500 and 1516.</p>
            <p>In <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doctors and learned men.</p>
            <p>D. <hi>Iohn Colet,</hi> Deane of Paules, who was a great labourer for reformation in the Church, and in his Sermons bitterly inueighed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt inhibition of Prieſts mariage, pilgrimages, and diuers other abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the popiſh Church: for which hee was much perſecuted by <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Fitz-Iames,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London. Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etex Regiſtr. Fitz Eraſm. ep. ad Iodoc. Ion.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gulielmus Lillius. Gulielm. Grocinus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gulielm. Latimer. Thomas Lynacre.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Whole Congregations perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted for it.</p>
            <p>In the Dioceſſe of <hi>Lancolne,</hi> to the number of 437 perſons. <hi>Martyrol. p.</hi> 751, 752. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>London</hi> 68 perſons. <hi>p.</hi> 734. 745.</p>
            <p>Martyrs put to death for it.</p>
            <list>
               <item>VVill: Sweeting.</item>
               <item>Iohn Brewſter.</item>
               <item>Iohn Browne.</item>
               <item>Iokime Norman.</item>
               <item>Iohn Stileman.</item>
               <item>Thomas Man.</item>
               <item>Robert Coſin.</item>
               <item>Chriſtop. Shooma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ker</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:20231:9"/>
               <item>Robert Rane.</item>
               <item>Iohn Seriuener.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <head>Doctors and learned men.</head>
               <item>Iacobus Pauanus.</item>
               <item>Iohannes de Cadurco.</item>
               <item>Laurentius Crucens. Patet ex Criſp. &amp; pantal.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Congregations.</p>
            <p>Whole villages of them in the tract where the Alpes are ioyned with the Pyrenies. <hi>Peir. de Soan. in hiſt. Concil. Trident. p.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>Whole villages about <hi>Merindol.</hi> and the Country of <hi>Prouence. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrol. p.</hi> 859.</p>
            <list>
               <head>Martyrs.</head>
               <item>Dionyſius de Reaux.</item>
               <item>Iacobus Pauanus.</item>
               <item>Bartholomaeus Millen.</item>
               <item>Henricus Poile.</item>
               <item>Iohannes Chaſtellanus.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In <hi>Germany.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <head>Doctors and learned men.</head>
               <item>Leo Iuda.</item>
               <item>Iohannes Oxlinus.</item>
               <item>Vldericus Zuinglius.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Congregations.</head>
               <item>Tigurines.</item>
               <item>Bernates.</item>
               <item>Lucernates.</item>
               <item>Suicenſes.</item>
               <item>Vnderualii.</item>
               <item>Baſilienſes.</item>
               <item>Martyrol. p. <hi>791.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Martyrs.</head>
               <item>Petrus Spengler.</item>
               <item>Wolgangus Schurch.</item>
               <item>Leonardus Heilar.</item>
               <item>Wendelmuta Vidua.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were diuers about this time profeſſing the Proteſtants religion, who were by the Papiſts tearmed <hi>Pycards, Calyſtini,</hi> and <hi>Subutraques. Pier: de Soau.</hi> in his Hiſtorie of the Trent Councill, p. 3.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:20231:9"/>
               <head>Before this time, and before <hi>Luther</hi> was borne, there were profeſſors of the Proteſtants Religion betweene the yeares of our Lord, 1450 and 1500.</head>
               <p>In <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>REynold Peacocke</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi> who publikely preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the Pope, Fryers, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, and the whole leauen of popery. <hi>Thomas Gaſgorgu. lib. de dict. Theol. p.</hi> 3.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Martyrs.</head>
                  <item>William Tilſworth. Lawrence Gheſt.</item>
                  <item>Thomas Barnard. Babram.</item>
                  <item>Iames Mordon.</item>
                  <item>Ioane Boughton <hi>Mother to the Lady</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Young. <hi>Acts and Monum.</hi> in regu.</item>
                  <item>Henric. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Perſecuted for the ſame.</head>
                  <item>Iohn Blomeſton.</item>
                  <item>Richard Hegham.</item>
                  <item>Robert Crowther.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Smith.</item>
                  <item>Roger Browne.</item>
                  <item>Thomas Butler.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Falkes.</item>
                  <item>Richard Hilmin.</item>
                  <item>Margery Goit.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>With diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in</hi> Kent, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentrie <hi>and</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. ibid. p. <hi>713, 714.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>In <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philippus Comineas,</hi> a French Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoriagrapher, who ſpared not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue the vices in Popery, and to extol thoſe who oppoſed the ſame. <hi>Martyrol. p.</hi> 672.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohannes. Seleſtadienſis. Vide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Epiſt. ad Maximil. Imper. contra Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificios.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Antonius Mancinellus,</hi> who wrote an eloquent oration againſt the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie life, and wicked manners of the Pope and his Clergy; and for that cauſe had his tongue and hands cut off by the commandement of the Pope. <hi>Martyrol. p.</hi> 674.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> the eight was at often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance with the Pope. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 675.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Germanes in generall exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited their complaints againſt the Pope to the Emperor <hi>Maximilian,</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Martyrol. p.</hi> 672.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rodulphus Agricolae.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pontanus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Philippus Baroaldus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20231:10"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Georgius Valla.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iohannes Oſtenderpius.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Doctor <hi>Keiſerſpergius.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Doctor <hi>Andreas Proles. Ex Luc. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiand. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVeſelus Groningenſis</hi> wrote againſt popiſh penance, indulgences, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, workes of ſupererrogation, abuſes of the Maſſe, prayers for the dead, vowes, precepts of the Pope and Prelates, &amp;c. Hee was a man ſo famous and notable for his great learning and good life, that hee was commonly called, <hi>Lux mundi, The light of the world. Ex Noviomag. &amp; Martyrol. p.</hi> 670.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Georgius Pogiebrachius,</hi> Gouernor of that Kingdome vnder the young King <hi>Ladiſlaus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rochezana</hi> and diuers other Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers more, of whoſe conformity with vs in Religion, and ſeparation from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> wee may reade, <hi>Cocl. lib. de Huſ. &amp; Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrol. p.</hi> 662. <hi>Item ex Aene. Sylv. in Hiſtor. Bohem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohannes Baptiſta Mantuanus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Angelus Politianus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hermolaus Barbarus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohannes Picus Mirandula.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>This <hi>Picus</hi> Earle of <hi>Mirandula,</hi> being but a young man, went to <hi>Rome,</hi> and there ſet vp 90 concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be diſputed on, of which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers were about the Sacrament, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, &amp;c. quite contrary to the tenent of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> for which hee was perſecuted by the Pope and his Clergy. <hi>Luc. Oſiand. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>Martyrol. p.</hi> 740.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hieronimus Sauanorola</hi> an Italian Monke, ſorely inueighed againſt the corruption in Popery, maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned iuſtification by faith, that the communion ought to bee admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in both kinds; that indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and pardons of the Pope were of no effect; againſt auricular confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and the Popes Supremacy; for which cauſe he with two more who taught and preached the ſame toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him, were hanged at <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> and afterwards burnt to aſhes. <hi>Illiric. Catal. teſt. Martyrol. pag.</hi> 450.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:20231:10"/>
               <head>Before that time there are to be found profeſſors of the Proteſtant Religion, betweene the yeares 1400 &amp; 1450.</head>
               <p>In <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THe name of <hi>Lollards</hi> about this time was commonly knowne in <hi>England:</hi> That they and wee doe agree in the ſubſtance of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion may appeare, <hi>ex deſcript. ſect. Lollard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Norwich</hi> complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, how the number of them did here encreaſe. <hi>Martyrol. pag.</hi> 609.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Martyrs.</head>
                  <item>Rich. Houerden.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Gooſe.</item>
                  <item>Paul Craw.</item>
                  <item>William White.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Claidon.</item>
                  <item>Richard Turning.</item>
                  <item>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Iohn Oldcaſtle.</item>
                  <item>Lord Cobham.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Perſecuted and put to penance <hi>for that profeſsion.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>Iohn Burrell.</item>
                  <item>Thomas Moone.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Finch.</item>
                  <item>Nicholas Belward</item>
                  <item>Thomas Grimar.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Beuerley.</item>
                  <item>Thomas Pye.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Mendham.</item>
                  <item>Robert Shiruing.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Terrie.</item>
                  <item>Hugh Pie.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Parker.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Skilly.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Cooper.</item>
                  <item>Bartholmew That<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher.</item>
                  <item>Thomas Iames.</item>
                  <item>Alane Andrew.</item>
                  <item>William VVright.</item>
                  <item>Richard Fletcher.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Aberee.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Middleton.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Waid.</item>
                  <item>Richard Clerke.</item>
                  <item>Robert Beet.</item>
                  <item>Richard Page.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Warden.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Kinget.</item>
                  <item>Thomas Albeck.</item>
                  <item>William Bates.</item>
                  <item>VVill: Osbourne.</item>
                  <item>Robert Briggs.</item>
                  <item>VVilliam Marſh.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Goodwin.</item>
                  <item>Henry Bood.</item>
                  <item>Richard Horne.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Spire.</item>
                  <item>Richard King:</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>with diuers others, as wee may finde them named and recorded,</hi> Martyrolog. pag. <hi>608.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Redonenſit,</hi> a Frenchman by birth, came into <hi>Italy</hi> about the yeare 1433, and there ſeeing the corruptions of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> inueighed exceedingly againſt the ſame; preaching that the Church did lack reformation: that the <hi>Popes</hi> excommunication is not to bee fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and diuers things to the like effect: for which he was perſecuted by <hi>Pope Eugenius,</hi> and in the end de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graded, and burnt at <hi>Rome. Ex An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonin.</hi> 3. <hi>part. fol.</hi> 165.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicholaus Clemangis</hi> an Arch dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. <hi>De annot. non ſoluend.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laurentius Valla,</hi> a Roman Patrici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, &amp; Cannon of S. <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Lateran.
<pb facs="tcp:20231:11"/> Ex eius tractat. contra Ementit. Donat conſtat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Petrus de Ali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> Cardinall of <hi>Cambray. Tract. de reform. eccleſ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leonardus Aretinus. Ex eius libello in Hypocrit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nicholaus Pycennius <hi>an Italian Captaine.</hi> Ex orat. Arelacenſ. in Concil. Baſil.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Antonius Cornelius Lynnichanus. Ex orat. ad cler. Colon. de lubricitat. ſacerd.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Martyrs.</head>
                  <item>Henricus Grunfielder.</item>
                  <item>Henricus Ratgeber.</item>
                  <item>Iohannes Dracnderſius.</item>
                  <item>Petrus Thoraw.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Matheus Hager: <hi>of whom, and the doctrine for which they ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, we may reade, in</hi> Bali. cent. &amp; Martyrol. p. <hi>614.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Hus,</hi> Bachelor of Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, maintained as Articles in <hi>Prague,</hi> againſt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (in effect the ſame that we doe) for which hee was called to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Conſtance;</hi> where for perſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therein he was condemned, and afterwards burnt. <hi>Concil. Conſtant. &amp; Choclaeus Huſſ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hierome</hi> of <hi>Prague,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> of Arts, ſeconded <hi>Iohn Hus,</hi> in defence of the ſame doctrine, and followed him in martyrdome. <hi>Cocl. ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="54">54 Noblemen of <hi>Morauia</hi> wrote to the Councell of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of <hi>Iohn Hus,</hi> and <hi>Hierome</hi> of <hi>Prague,</hi> whoſe names, together with their Letter, are recorded, <hi>Marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rol. p.</hi> 587.</p>
               <p>A great part of the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia</hi> forſooke the <hi>Pope,</hi> &amp; claue to the doctrine which they had learned from <hi>Hus</hi> and <hi>Hierom. Cocle. ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ziſca,</hi> a noble <hi>Bohemian,</hi> with a great multitude of aſſociates, wage warre againſt the Papiſts, and throw Images and Idols out of their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, <hi>Coch. ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:20231:11"/>
               <head>Before that time there may be ſeene profeſſors of the Proteſtants Religion, betweene the yeares 1350 and. 1400.</head>
               <p>In <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ROger VVimbleton,</hi> whoſe lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Sermon againſt diuers points of Popery, preached at <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſſe, <hi>Anno</hi> 1389 is extant, <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrolog. pag.</hi> 503.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn VVickliffe,</hi> publique Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Diuinitie in the Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Oxford,</hi> a famous learned man, whoſe doctrine agreeing with ours, may bee ſeene in his propoſitions recorded, <hi>Martyrol. pag.</hi> 414.</p>
               <p>This <hi>VVickliffe</hi> had many fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites at that time, eſpecially <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Gant,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> Lord <hi>Percie;</hi> the one of Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> the other Marſhall of <hi>England, Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Vniuerſitie of <hi>Oxford, pag.</hi> 408, and many in the Parliament, <hi>Anno</hi> 43 of <hi>Edward</hi> 3, did adhere vnto him. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Letters of King <hi>Richard</hi> the third, and the Acts of Parliament then declare that this doctrine was dayly preached in Churches and Churchyards, at which were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent great multitudes of people. <hi>Anno</hi> 5. <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Martyrs.</head>
                  <item>VVilliam Santree.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Badbic.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Perſecuted for the ſame <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>Philip Repington,</item>
                  <item>Nicholas Hartford.</item>
                  <item>William Thorpe.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Puruie.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Edwards.</item>
                  <item>William Swinderby, <hi>&amp; diuers others.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Act. &amp; Mon in</hi> vit. Rich</item>
                  <item>Walter Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n.</item>
                  <item>Iohn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eeker.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Sey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</item>
                  <item>Dauid Cotray.</item>
               </list>
               <p>In <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gerardus</hi> a Deacon.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Henricus de Iota.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henricus de Haſſia,</hi> 140 of thoſe who adhered to the doctrine of the <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> were about this time put to death in the Prouince of <hi>Narbone, Maſſae hiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A great number more about this time were burnt in <hi>France</hi> for the like cauſe, and were nickna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, Publicans, Puritans, Pate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines. <hi>Houedom. hiſt. &amp; Martyrol. pag.</hi> 387.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20231:12"/>
               <p>In <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Taulerus,</hi> a preacher of <hi>Argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohannes Montziger</hi> Rector of the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Vlme,</hi> who openly in the ſchooles, impugned the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Tranſubſtanciation. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrol. p.</hi> 386.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Conradus Hager.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rhider.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>About the yeare of our Lord 1390, thirty ſix Citizens of <hi>Mentz</hi> were burnt for the doctrine of the <hi>VValdenſes,</hi> and holding the <hi>Pope</hi> to be Antichriſt, and relying vpon the Scriptures, and not vpon the traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Church of <hi>Rome. Braſ. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. St. Martyrol. p.</hi> 587.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicholas Orem,</hi> whoſe Sermon before the Pope and his Cardinals, <hi>Anno</hi> 1546; fauoureth of our doctrine. <hi>Extat Martyrol. p.</hi> 382.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohannes de Ganduno.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Andreas à Caſtro.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dantes Florentinus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Franciſcus Petrarcha.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohannes de rupe Sciſſa.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohannes de Caſtellione.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohannes de Poliaco.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>In <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Matthias Pariſienſis,</hi> a Bohemian by birth, about the yeare 1370 wrote a booke of Antichriſt, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him already to bee come, and that the <hi>Pope</hi> is the ſame. <hi>Martyrol. p.</hi> 586.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iacobus Milnenſis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Miletius.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The Vniuerſitie of <hi>Prague</hi> in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of <hi>VVickliffe, ibid.</hi> 420</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter Paine,</hi> a Scholler of <hi>VVick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffe,</hi> came into <hi>Bohemia,</hi> &amp; brought with him <hi>VVickliffs</hi> bookes which were in quantitie as great as Saint <hi>Auguſtines</hi> workes. <hi>Hiſtor de Huſ. lib.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>Petrus de Corbaria.</item>
                  <item>Franciſcus de Arcatara. Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relog.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:20231:12"/>
               <head>Before that time there may be ſeene profeſſors of the Proteſtants Religion, betweene the yeares 1300 and 1350.</head>
               <p>In <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ARmachanus,</hi> ſometimes a Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in <hi>Oxford,</hi> afterward Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Armach,</hi> and Primate of <hi>Ireland;</hi> who before Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the 8 his Cardinals diſputed nine concluſions againſt the Friers. <hi>Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffe in Trid.</hi> Beſides that, hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted againſt diuers other abuſes in the Popiſh Church. <hi>Martyrol. p.</hi> 378 for which he ſuſtained diuers trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, by meanes of the <hi>Pope</hi> and his Cardinals. <hi>Martyrol. page</hi> 375.</p>
               <p>That there were diuers others a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this time of that Religion here in <hi>England,</hi> may appeare out of a book then compiled and entituled, <hi>The complaint of the Ploughman. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. Martyrol. p.</hi> 366.</p>
               <p>In <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philip</hi> the French King wrote a Letter of defiance againſt <hi>Boniface</hi> the 8. <hi>Nichol. Triuet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Nagaretta.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Pleſiano,</hi> in the French Kings name ſolemnly protected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Pope. Martyr. p.</hi> 314.</p>
               <p>The Nobles, Prelates, and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>France</hi> cenſure the abuſes of the Papacy, <hi>ibid. p.</hi> 315. 318. 324.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rudo</hi> Duke of <hi>Bourgundy</hi> about the yeare 1348, diſſwadeth the French King from permitting in his Realme the Popes Decrees and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretals, whoſe ſage counſell then gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, as yet remaineth among the French Kings Records. <hi>Teſtatur Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rol. Molinaeus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gulielmus Ockam</hi> about the yeare 1326 wrote in defence of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Ludouicus</hi> againſt the <hi>Pope,</hi> who wrote alſo diuers other Books in which he confuteth the vſurped Supremacie of the <hi>Pope,</hi> and entring into mention of the <hi>Popes</hi> Decrees extrauagant, declareth how little regard is to bee giuen thereto. <hi>Iohn Sleid. lib.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lricus Hangenor,</hi> Treaſurer to the Emperor <hi>Ludouicus</hi> publiquely op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed himſelfe againſt the <hi>Popes</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings. <hi>Martyrol. p</hi> 358.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregorius Ariminenſis</hi> about the yeare of our Lord 1346, maintained the ſame doctrine of grace and free will, which the Proteſtants at this day doe, and diſſented from the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and Sophiſters, counting them worſe then <hi>Pelagians. Ex Trithemio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Petrus de Bruis</hi> who laid the Axe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20231:13"/> to the root of Popery, and in ſet-Treatiſes oppoſed moſt of his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuments. <hi>Pap. Meſſ.</hi> in <hi>Bonif.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Luitpoldus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Andreas Landenſis.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>In <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marſilius Patauinus,</hi> in his booke entituled, <hi>Defenſor pacis,</hi> held theſe concluſions. 1, That the <hi>Pope</hi> hath none authority ouer other Biſhops, much leſſe ouer the Emperour. 2. That the Word of God ought to bee iudge in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall. 3, The Clergie and Pope ought to be ſubiect to Magiſtrates. 4, That Chriſt is the head of the Church, and that hee neuer appointed any <hi>Pope</hi> to be his general Vicar. 5, That the mariage of Prieſts is lawfull. 6, That S. <hi>Peter</hi> was neuer at <hi>Rome.</hi> 7, That the Clergie of <hi>Rome</hi> is a den of theeues. 8, That the Popes doctrine leadeth to eternall damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Defenſ. pac.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aligerius.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Andreas de Caſtro.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohannes Rochetaylada (Henrici de Erford</hi> nameth him <hi>Haybalus</hi>) prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched openly that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was the whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the Pope with his Cardinals to bee the very Antichriſt. And being for the ſame brought before the Popes face, conſtantly did perſeuere in the ſame, ſaying, that hee was comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by God to publiſh the ſame. <hi>Froyſard. Volum.</hi> 1. <hi>chap.</hi> 211. <hi>&amp; Martyrol. pag.</hi> 360.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:20231:13"/>
               <head>Before that time there may bee ſeene profeſſors of the Proteſtants Religion, betweene the yeares 1250 &amp; 1300.</head>
               <p>In <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PEter</hi> the ſonne of, <hi>Caſsiodore</hi> wrote a zealous Epiſtle to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> dehorting it from the tyranny of the Church of <hi>Rome. Ex vetuſt. Chron. Alban. extat. Martyrol.</hi> 323.</p>
               <p>The Popes inhibition was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed in <hi>England, Anno Domini</hi> 1294.</p>
               <p>Diuers alſo about this time were accuſed here in <hi>England</hi> for adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to the opinion of the <hi>Walden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Turris Lond. in record. reconcil. inter regem &amp; Baron.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gulielmus Altiſſiodorenſis,</hi> an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Schoolman, in whoſe ſummes many points of popiſh doctrine are ſtrongly oppoſed and confuted. <hi>Naucler. vol.</hi> 2. <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohannes Semeca,</hi> Prouoſt of <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſtat,</hi> was about this time excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, and depriued of his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, for reſiſting Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the fourth, gathering certain exactions in <hi>Germanie,</hi> who therefore ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed from the Pope to a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councell, and had many great fauourers of his ſide. <hi>Martyrol. pag.</hi> 287.</p>
               <p>In <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gulielmus de S. Amore,</hi> Maſter in <hi>Paris,</hi> and chiefe ruler in that Vniuerſitie, hee wrote a booke <hi>de periculis Eccleſiae,</hi> wherein he main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth 39 concluſions againſt the Papiſts; but eſpecially againſt the Friers. <hi>Magdeb. cent.</hi> 13. c. 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Robertus Gallus,</hi> borne of a Noble parentage, about the yeare 1290, wrote diuers propheſies againſt the Pope &amp; church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in a booke of viſions. In the firſt Chap. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hee painteth forth the Pope like an Idol. In the twelfth Chapter like a Serpent. In the thirteenth, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembleth the ſtate of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to a body, whoſe head is dry, leane, and withered like a logge of wood. In another place, hee compareth the Schoole-men in their ſubtill queſtions and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions to a man, who hauing fine Manchet bread, and pure Wine ſet before him, doth not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20231:14"/> chuſe rather to gnaw vpon an hard and flinty ſtone. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrol. pag.</hi> 292.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Petrus Iohannes,</hi> a <hi>Minorite,</hi> about the yeare 1290, taught and maintained many things againſt the Pope, prouing that he was An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt: and the Synagogue of <hi>Rome,</hi> the great whore of <hi>Babylon. Nichol. Emer. in lib. inquiſit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arnoldus de Villa noua,</hi> a Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard by birth, about the yeare 1252 was by the <hi>Pope</hi> condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for an Hereticke, becauſe hee wrote againſt the corruptions of the Romiſh Church; his preaching was to this effect. Firſt, that the <hi>Pope</hi> and his Clergie ſeduce the world, like Satan, from the truth of Chriſt. Secondly, Faith (as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts require it) is no better then the Deuils faith. Thirdly, that the <hi>Pope</hi> leadeth men to Hell. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that Cloiſterers are void of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. Fiftly, that Maſſes are not to be celebrated, and that they ought not to ſacrifice for the dead, with many other propoſitions to the like effect. <hi>Magdeb. cent.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiad. cent.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:20231:14"/>
               <head>Before that time there may be ſeene profeſſors of the Proteſtants Religion betweene the yeares 1200 and 1250</head>
               <p>In <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>RObert Groſthead</hi> Biſhop of Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne, a man of great learning and godlineſſe, who liued in the daies of Pope <hi>Innocentius</hi> the fourth, and conſtantly reſiſted his vnlawfull demands, as by name, the inueſting of a young Italian boy whom the Pope had recommended vnto him, to be admitted into the next vacant Prebend in his Dioceſſe: for his ſharp reprouing the Pope of Rome, and powerful preaching againſt the corruptions in that Sea, hee was commonly called <hi>Malleus Romano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, The Hammer of the Romanes:</hi> for his courage and doctrine, the Pope was much incenſed againſt him, and ſware that he would hurle him downe to ſuch a confuſion, that he ſhould be made a gazing ſtocke to all the world: notwithſtanding all which, this good Biſhop died peaceably. And when as after his death the Pope would haue caſt his bones out of Chriſtian buriall, in the night following the ſaid Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop ſeemed in a viſion to appeare before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m, and ſmiting him with his Crozier-ſtaffe on his right ſide, with a ſterne looke and terrible voice to ſay vnto him, <hi>O thou ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, lazy, bald, doting Pope, haſt thou purpoſed to caſt my bones out of the Church? God will not ſuffer thee to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile: woe to thee that deſpiſeſt, for thou ſhalt be deſpiſed.</hi> And ſo ſeeming to depart, the Pope was found the next morning in a manner halfe dead. <hi>Math. Pariſ. &amp; Martyrol. p.</hi> 295, 296.</p>
               <p>In <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laurentius Anglicus,</hi> an Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man borne, but Student in Paris, &amp; of prime eſteeme in that Vniuerſity, wrote againſt the Pope, affirming that in him and his Prelates Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt was already come. <hi>Martyrol. p.</hi> 292.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Almaricus</hi> a Doctor of Paris, was burnt for withſtanding altars, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, inuocation of Saints, tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation. <hi>Car. Chron.</hi> 1202.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Sweden.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About the yeare of our Lord 1240 there were in Sweden many Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers who in their Sermons inuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the Pope, affirming the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20231:15"/> Pope and his Biſhops to bee here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks and Symoniacks, and that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh prieſts were meere ſeducers, that the Popes curſe was not to bee dreaded, and his indulgences were meere fopperies. <hi>Ex Chronic. Abbat. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſperg. Crantz. lib.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Frederick <hi>the ſecond reſiſted the Popes vſurpations, exiled his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie out of Germany, and fought againſt him proſperouſly.</hi> Mat. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſ. p. <hi>71.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sygefridus Seginoburgenſit, Rudice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Rhathenicenſis, Conradus Friſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſis, <hi>Biſhops of Boiora ioyne with the Emperour againſt the Pope.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent. lib. <hi>5.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Euarardus Inuanenſis <hi>an Archbiſhop in Germany ſpake thus of the Pope in an Aſſembly of Biſhops at Regen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpurg:</hi> He vnder the colour of religion layeth the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the kingdome of Antichriſt: Theſe prieſts of Babylon will reigne alone, they can endure no equall, they will neuer reſt vntill they haue trampled all things vnder their feet: he ſitteth in the Temple of God, and is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted aboue all that is worſhipped. Thus doth that child of perdition (whom they vſe to call Antichriſt) in whoſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head is written the name of blaſphemy, I am a god, and cannot erre. Auent. lib. <hi>7.</hi> p. <hi>546.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:20231:15"/>
               <head>Before that time there may be ſeene profeſſors of the Proteſtants Religion betweene the yeares 1150 and 1200.</head>
               <p>In <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>GErhardus</hi> and <hi>Dulcinus Nauar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renſis</hi> about this time preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the Church of Rome, defending and maintaining, firſt, That prayer was not more holy in one place then another: ſecondly, That the Pope was Antichriſt, and Rome the very Whoore of Babylon prefigured in the Apocalyps. Theſe two about the yeare 1158 brought 30 other of their own opinion with them ouer into England, who by the commandement of the King &amp; Prelates, were burnt in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, &amp; ſo driuen out of the Realm. <hi>Rob. Giſburn. Illiricus</hi> ſaith they were afterwards ſlaine by the Pope. <hi>Illir. Catol. Martyrol. p.</hi> 83.</p>
               <p>In <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Waldenſes</hi> or <hi>Pauperes de Lug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duno,</hi> ſo called from one <hi>Waldus</hi> a man of great ſubſtance in the City of Lyons, who about the yeare 1160 taking occaſion by the ſudden death of one with whom hee was walking, beganne with a carefull ſtudie to reforme his life, and to this end ſtudied the Scriptures diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and taught the true knowledge of Gods word to as many as reſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto him. In ſhort ſpace the number of thoſe who ioyned with him came to thouſands, who were diſperſed abroad into diuers parts of the world: Theſe were miſerably perſecuted by the Pope and his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. <hi>Hiſt. de Waldenſ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Raymund</hi> Earle of Tholouſe for taking part with them was wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully vexed and diſinherited by the Pope. <hi>Mat. Pariſ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <head>The Religion of the Waldenſes.</head>
                  <item>1 They held that the Pope is not greater then another Biſhop.</item>
                  <item>2 That there is no purgatory.</item>
                  <item>3 That it is in vaine to pray for the dead.</item>
                  <item>4 That Maſſes for the dead are the inuentions of couetous prieſts.</item>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:20231:16"/>
                  <item>5 That images, hallowing of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and other creatures, are ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious.</item>
                  <item>6 That the word of God ſhould be truly preached vnto all men.</item>
                  <item>7 That Fryers ſhrift, and the vſe of the oile in Baptiſme, are the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions of men.</item>
                  <item>8 They contemned the Maſſe, &amp; all that appertained to it.</item>
                  <item>9 They miſliked the ſingle life of votaries, and the diſtinction of daies and meats.</item>
                  <item>10 They defended the reading of Scripture by the Laitie.</item>
                  <item>11 They had but two ſacraments.</item>
                  <item>12 That the Communion ſhould be adminiſtred in both kinds. <hi>Nauc. vol.</hi> 2. <hi>g.</hi> 900.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hildebertus</hi> Archbiſhop of Tours about this time taxed the pride of the Pope, and being an excellent Poet, made this diſtich of Rome:
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbs foelix, ſi vel dominis vrbs illa careret,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vel dominis eſſet turpe carere fide.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>Happy would this City be,</l>
                     <l>If wanting lords her ſelfe were free,</l>
                     <l>Or hauing Lords in dignitie,</l>
                     <l>Theſe wanted not true honeſty.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fredericke Barbaroſſa</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, about the yeare 1150 oppoſed himſelfe againſt the Pope, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding appeales to Rome, &amp; the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Legates from thence into Germany, and other trickes of the papall pride. A great part of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie tooke part with him. <hi>Naucl. vol.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 836. <hi>gen.</hi> 39.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About this time, <hi>Anſelme</hi> Biſhop of Haremburg, being ſent from <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharius</hi> to <hi>Calo Iohannes</hi> Emperor of Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinople, among other things he diſputed much of the ſupremacy of the Romane Biſhop, <hi>Nichetes</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Nicodemia excellently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted againſt him, and confuted his arguments, maintaining that the pride of the Romiſh Church was the cauſe of ſo many ſchiſmes and hereſies which were then abroad in the world. <hi>Ext. in Naucl. vol.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 900 <hi>&amp; in Patr. Sympſ. hiſt. of the Church. p.</hi> 433.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:20231:16"/>
               <head>Before that time there may bee ſeene profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> Religion betweene the yeeres 1100. and 1150.</head>
               <p>In <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>THeobald</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> with the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates of <hi>England,</hi> in a Councell held at <hi>London, anno</hi> 16. <hi>Regni Stephani regis,</hi> decreed that Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſhould liue more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcreetly; that Prieſts ſhould not bee Rulers ouer worldly matters, that they ſhould teach their flockes more diligently, and that the people ſhould read the Scriptures, and learne the Lords Prayer, &amp; the Creed in Engliſh. <hi>Malſmb. Chron.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>King <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, and his Nobles, were euen at the point to forſake the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, <hi>Patet ex Epiſt. Anſelm. ad Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal. Pap. &amp; Martyrol. pag.</hi> 177.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Liucolnienſis</hi> gaue this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of a Frier; <hi>A Frier is a dead Carkaſſe riſen out of his Graue, wrap'd in a winding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheet, and carried among men by the Diuell.</hi> Wichleif. <hi>in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alog. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 26. <hi>pag.</hi> 143.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Almaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>HIldegard</hi> a Nunne and a Propheteſſe, liuing about the yeere 1146. moſt bitterly reprehended the abhominable life of the Pope and his Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, inueighing againſt the greedie ſubtill proceeding of Friers; denouncing woe vnto thoſe who ſuffer themſelues to be ſeduced by them, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telling the horrible deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church of <hi>Rome. Hiſtor. Iornal. &amp; Martyrol. p.</hi> 182. <hi>&amp;</hi> 237.</p>
               <p>In <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>BErnard</hi> Abbot of <hi>Cluxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val</hi> born in <hi>Burgundy,</hi> liued about this time, who although (liuing in a moſt corrupt age) hee was exceeding ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in ſome points, yet freely reproued diuers corruptions then comming on, hee is cleare with vs againſt the conceipt of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20231:17"/> the Virgin <hi>Maries</hi> Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on free from ſinne, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, <hi>Ex Epiſt.</hi> 179. <hi>ad Cam. Lugdon.</hi> Againſt Merites, <hi>Ser.</hi> 1. <hi>de Annunciat.</hi> Againſt Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by workes, <hi>Serm.</hi> 22. <hi>in Cantic.</hi> Againſt Free will, <hi>Lib. de Grana. &amp; lib. Arb.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſeuenfold number of Sacraments. <hi>Ser.</hi> 1. <hi>de coen. Dom</hi> Againſt the vncertaintie of Saluation. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 107. Againſt the Popes Greatneſſe in Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralities. <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>conſid. ad Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen.</hi> Alſo hee admoniſhed Count <hi>Theobald,</hi> who beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed great matters in building of Abbies and Churches, that he ſhould rather ſupport them which are of the houſhold of Faith, and bee carefull to build the euerlaſting Tabernacle. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 107.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Flanders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>ABout this time was one burnt in <hi>Antwerp,</hi> for Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching againſt the reall preſence in the Sacrament. <hi>Maſſan. Chron. lib.</hi> 16. <hi>anno</hi> 1124.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Germanie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>HEnry</hi> the fifth Emperor, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Paſchalis</hi> then Pope, maintayned his owne right of making Biſhops, and other Priuiledges that belonged to his Anceſtors, which the Pope vſurped. <hi>Nauder. vol.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 807. <hi>Segon. anno</hi> 1111.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Italie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arnulphus</hi> an eloquent Preacher came to <hi>Rome</hi> about this time, and in his Preaching reproues the vicious life of the Popiſh Clergie; hee is ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to bee the Author of the Booke called <hi>Opus Triparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> which containeth a great complaint of the enormities and abuſes in the Church, of the number of their Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, of the curious ſinging in Cathedrall Churches, of the rabble of begging Friers, of the vnchaſt voluptuous beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour of Churchmen; and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, wiſheth reformation to begin at the Sanctuary; for the which the hatred of the Pope and his Clergie was ſo much incenſed againſt him, that they layd priuie wait for him, tooke him and drowned him. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrol. pag.</hi> 181. <hi>Sabellius</hi> and <hi>Platina,</hi> ſay they hanged him. <hi>Platin. in vit. Honor.</hi> 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:20231:17"/>
               <head>Before that time there may bee ſeene profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> Religion, betweene the yeares, 1050. and 1100.</head>
               <p>In <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>ABout this time (ſaith <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew Paris</hi>) The King of <hi>England</hi> fauored not much the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe of their impudent and vnſatiable exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, neither would he ſuffer any of his Subiects to goe to <hi>Rome,</hi> alledging theſe wordes in the Author thus expreſſed, <hi>Quod Petri non inhaerent veſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gijs, praemijs inhiantes, non eius poteſtatem retinent, cuius ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitatem probantur non imitari. Math. Pariſ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>BErengarius</hi> Archdeacon of <hi>Angeow,</hi> about the yeare 1060. withſtood the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation newly hatched in the Councell of <hi>Lateran.</hi> And although by the violence of the Pope and his Clergie hee was driuen to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation, yet after his Death many adhered to his opinion. <hi>Malſmb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Germanie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>HEnry</hi> the third Emperour, withſtood <hi>Hildebrand</hi> the Pope and his vſurped Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie. <hi>Sigeb. Chron. in anno</hi> 1077.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Walenam</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Merg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg. Merian. Scot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sigefridus</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Mentz. Martyrol. pag.</hi> 161.</p>
               <p>The Councell of <hi>Wormes. Aventin. Anal. lib.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>The Councell of <hi>Brixia</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the yeare 1083. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the Pope to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and withdrew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from his Authoritie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abbas vſb. &amp; Martyrol. pag.</hi> 164.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:20231:18"/>
               <p>In <hi>Italie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>NIcetus</hi> an <hi>Italian</hi> Abbot.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Benno.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Vgobaldus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Leo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohannes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Petrus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Natro.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theodinus.</hi> Cardinals, with diuers other Biſhops &amp; Prieſts of <hi>Italie,</hi> forſooke the Pope, and adhered to the Emperour. <hi>Auent, Anal. lib.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sygebert,</hi> a Chronicle writer of thoſe times, taxeth the Popes Excommunication of Princes and abſoluing their Subiects from obedience, of noueltie and hereſie. <hi>Sygeb. in anno</hi> 1088.</p>
               <p>And thus (through Gods aſſiſtance) wee haue traced out the footſteps of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> Religion from <hi>Luther</hi> to <hi>Beren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garius,</hi> from the dayes of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, vnto the comming in of King <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror. And wee haue found a cloud of witneſſes in <hi>England, France, Germanie, Italie, Spaine, Bohemia,</hi> and diuers other Countries, for the ſpace almoſt of Fiue hundred yeeres ſucceſſiuely profeſſing and maintayning the ſame, whereby wee may plainly ſee that our Religion was long before <hi>Luther,</hi> and that they were not all <hi>Papiſts</hi> that liued in the Chriſtian world, before <hi>Luthers</hi> dayes, as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> fooliſhly doe traduce. Now let vs follow the ſame tract a little higher, and make enquirie whether we may not finde the ſame in the Elder dayes, and in the yeares of former Generations, euen to the time in which <hi>Poperie</hi> firſt began, and before the hatching of the ſame; which (by the like aſſiſtance of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God) I doubt not to performe in that which followeth.</p>
               <p>But now for a while in the next enſuing Centuries, we ſhall, I confeſſe, behold the Church of Chriſt, like the Sunne obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in a cloud; <hi>Popery</hi> being about this time in the height of her Pride,<note place="margin">Reuel. 17.2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>When the Kings of the earth gaue their power and ſtrength vnto the Beaſt, and the Nations were drunken with the Cup of that Babiloniſh Strumpet.</hi> Beſides, that (euen as our Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries themſelues acknowledge) thoſe times were barren and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure times, becauſe there were few good Writers in thoſe times which did Record the occurrents of the times; And therefore there cannot be expected ſo large Catologue in theſe, as wee
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20231:18"/> haue, either in the dayes before, or in theſe latter Times. Yet bleſſed be the name of the Lord, he hath not left himſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out witneſſeſſe, euen in theſe moſt obſcure times, But there we may meet with diuers, who followed the ſame way, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the ſame Truth, which we <hi>Proteſtants</hi> now doe, as may appeare by the Induction following.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Betweene the yeares 1000. and 1050.</head>
               <p>In England.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marianus Scotus</hi> an Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riographer, who liued in the daies of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor, and ſpared not in his writings to reproue the practiſe of Papiſts in thoſe daies. <hi>Maxian. Scot. hiſt. &amp; Martyrol. p.</hi> 149.</p>
               <p>Vnder the raigne of King <hi>Canutus</hi> (although ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did in this land wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abound, yet diuers points of the Proteſtants religion, as Iuſtification by Faith, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in all ſorts of people to Magiſtrates, in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as we now hold them, was then profeſſed, as may appeare by <hi>Canutus</hi> his Lawes, <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrol p.</hi> 148. <hi>&amp; ex Iornal. hiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luthericus</hi> an Archbiſhop in <hi>France,</hi> about this time de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the reall preſence in the Sacrament. <hi>Baron: Ann.</hi> 1004. <hi>n.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Glaber Rodulphus</hi> wrote, how that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould haue nothing to doe in another mans Dioceſſe. The which he alſo ſaith was the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of all the French Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats. <hi>Heſp. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>Quem refert Baronius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Germanie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rodulphus Ardens</hi> Preached againſt the popiſh opinion of Merits, as appeareth out of his <hi>Homilie, Dominic. in Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint:</hi> and in his 1. <hi>Hom. in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minic Trin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Rodulphus Ardens</hi> alſo taught, that there is no a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie in vs to keepe the Law, As may appeare out of his 2. <hi>Hom. in</hi> 18. <hi>dom. Trinit.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:20231:19"/>
               <head>Betweene the yeares 950. and 1000.</head>
               <p>In <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Cleargie of <hi>England</hi> in a Councell held, 975. withſtood <hi>Dunſtans</hi> prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Prieſts Marriage, <hi>Hen. lib.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fatholdus</hi> (whom ſome call <hi>Ethreredus</hi>) a learned man of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſo euidently by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Fathers proued, that Marriage was lawfull to men in ſpirituall offices, that <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans</hi> Miracle was reputed an illuſion of the Deuill, <hi>Hiſt. Magdeb. cent.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aelfricus</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterburie</hi> about the yeare 996. wrote an Epiſtle to <hi>Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Shirburne</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the houſling of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament; And another Epiſtle to <hi>Wolſtan</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Yorke</hi> againſt Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Which with a Sermon of his in the Saxon tongue are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant. <hi>Martyrol. p.</hi> 1040. 1401. 1042.</p>
               <p>In <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fulco</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Rhemes</hi> vttering his minde freely in a Councell held at <hi>Rhemes</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Raigne of <hi>Carolus Simplex,</hi> againſt the abuſes of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and for ſeeking reformation of the Church, was ſlaine in that Counſell by <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>inemarus. Ex Rhem. Concil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luitprandus</hi> a famous Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoriographer, in the daies of <hi>Otho</hi> the 1. wrote againſt the Pope. <hi>Epiſt. Luitpr. ad Regino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundus Epiſc. Hiſp.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Germanie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Otho</hi> the Great Depoſed Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> the 13. and aſſumed into his owne hands the nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and making of Popes, which was a manifeſt reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance againſt the growth of the primacie. <hi>Sigon. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>ann.</hi> 963.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:20231:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theophilact</hi> is thought to haue liued about this time, he was Biſhop of <hi>Bulgaria,</hi> and wrote Greeke Commentaries vpon the Euangeliſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Hee ſaid <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhould ſpring in the decay of the Roman Empire; and of Marriage, that it was honourable, and a ſtep to the Chaire of a Biſhop. <hi>Theophilact.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Betweene the yeares 900. and 950.</head>
               <p>In <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Engliſh Clergie about this time were very perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie againſt the Reall preſence. <hi>Oſbernun vit. St. Oden. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrol. p.</hi> 1029.</p>
               <p>The Lawes of King <hi>Athel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan,</hi> and of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Elder, doe plainely ſhew, that the Kings of <hi>England</hi> at that time gouerned as well in cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Eccleſiaſticall as ciuill. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract. è legibus. Rex Athelſt. Martyrol. p.</hi> 1039.</p>
               <p>In <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reynerus</hi> confeſſeth, that about this time there were in <hi>France,</hi> diuers of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors of the <hi>Abbigenſes,</hi> which euen in thoſe daies held their opinions, <hi>Illyr. tom,</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 548.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Germanie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The booke entituled <hi>Faſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus temporum</hi> complaineth of the manifold abuſes which about this time were in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed diuers of the Germans to write, and to inueigh againſt the ſame, <hi>Faſcic. temp. p.</hi> 68.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:20231:20"/>
               <head>Betweene the yeares 850. and 900.</head>
               <p>In <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>KIng <hi>Alfred</hi> cauſed the Pſalter and diuers other parcels of holy Scripture to be tranſlated into the Engliſh tongue, that the Engliſh might be the better acquainted with the ſame. <hi>Gulielm. de Regiby. Angl.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohannes Scotus</hi> a great lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man was famous about this time, he wrote a Booke <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and an other <hi>De corpore &amp; ſanguine Domini,</hi> for the which, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his Poſitions contrarie to the opinion of the popiſh Church, he was accuſed of the Pope for an Hereticke, and at the laſt was murthered. <hi>Iornal. c.</hi> 171. <hi>Martyrol. p.</hi> 130.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Noetus</hi> and <hi>Werefrithus</hi> at the ſame time here in <hi>England</hi> were of the ſame opinions. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Germanie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Huldericke</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Auſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> about the yeare 867. wrote an Epiſtle to Pope <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas</hi> the 1. prouing by ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall reaſons, that Prieſts ought not to bee reſtrained from Marriage, <hi>Ex tat haec E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. Martyrol. p.</hi> 125. <hi>Illyric. in Catal. Meminit etiam huius Epiſtolae Aeneas Siluius in ſua perigr, &amp; Germaniae deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Biſhop of <hi>Rauenna</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo about this time wrote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Supremacie of the Biſhp of <hi>Rome. Anaſt. in vit. Nich.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Michael</hi> the Emperour, and <hi>Photius</hi> the Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> ſtoutly reſiſted the Popes ſupremacie, in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of whom the Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors of Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> the 2. came to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> where a Councell being gathered by <hi>Baſilius</hi> againſt <hi>Photius,</hi> great policie was vſed in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, to haue all things framed to the content of the Romiſh Biſhop, <hi>Michael</hi> was ſlaine,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20231:20"/> 
                  <hi>Photius</hi> depoſed, and to his place <hi>Taratius</hi> a great defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the adoration of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges is preferred. <hi>Exopiſt. Nich. ann. Mich. Anaſtaſ. in vit. Nich.</hi> 1.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Betweene the yeares 800. and 850.</head>
               <p>In <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Mailros.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Claudius Clemens.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Two learned men of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi> ſent by King <hi>Achaius</hi> to <hi>Charles</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> and the firſt profeſſors of Learning in the Vniuerſity founded in <hi>Paris;</hi> Theſe two were much diſliked by the Prelates of the Romiſh Church, becauſe they would not aſſent to all the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions of that Church in an age ſo miſerably deformed. <hi>Patrick, Sympſ. hiſt</hi> of the <hi>Ch.</hi> 2. Booke. <hi>cent.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 386.</p>
               <p>In <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Claudius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Tours</hi> oppoſed himſelfe againſt the adoration of Images, Inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Saints, Pilgrimage, &amp;c. <hi>Ionas Aurel. de Cult: Imag.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Albertus Ballus</hi> a Biſhop in <hi>France</hi> was Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Pope <hi>Zacharie,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee held diuers things contrary to the Romiſh ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions. <hi>Hiſt. Magd. cent.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Germanie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lotharius</hi> the Emperour reduced the Pope to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the Empire, and ſent three Arch-Biſhops, twenty Biſhops, and diuers noble men to <hi>Rome,</hi> who diſputed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Pope and confuted him. <hi>Anaſtaſ. vit. Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Serg.</hi> 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:20231:21"/>
               <head>Betweene the yeares 750. and 800.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bertram</hi> that famous lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man, very skilfull in the Scriptures, and of a life vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blamable, as <hi>Trithemius</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth of him, wrote a B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oke about this time againſt Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, which booke is now extant. <hi>Trithem. Catul. ſcript.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alcwinus</hi> and the Biſhops of <hi>England</hi> wrote an Epiſtle ſubſtantially grounded out of holy Scripture about this time to the French King againſt ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp of Images and other popiſh practiſes. <hi>Continuatio Bedae in ann.</hi> 792.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Germanie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> the great aſſembled a Counſell at <hi>Franckeford</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the yeare 794. wherein was condemned the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of Images <hi>Concil. Fr.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Charles</hi> alſo cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a booke to be made againſt the 2 <hi>Nicene</hi> Counſell (where the worſhipping of Images was decreed) with another ſet forth by <hi>Ludouicus</hi> his Son to the ſame effect; Both which are to bee ſeene at this day. <hi>Rhegino. Chron.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the yeare of our Lord 755. and in the 13. yeare of the Raigne of <hi>Conſtantinus Copronymus</hi> a generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of 338. Biſhops were aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled at <hi>Constantinople,</hi> in which Councell the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of Images is condemned, and the placing of them in O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratories and Temples was forbidden. <hi>Zonar. Tem.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 88.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Betweene the yeares 700. and 750.</head>
               <p>In <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beda</hi> tranſlated <hi>St. Iohns</hi> Goſpel into Engliſh. <hi>Malmſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Adelbartus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Clemens.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Theſe two here in <hi>England</hi> about this time preached
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20231:21"/> againſt the Popes Supremacie, Traditions, Images, Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Maſſes for the dead, and in defence of Prieſts marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age. <hi>Illyr. Catal. teſt. tom.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 633.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Philipicus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Leo Iſaurus.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Two Emperours of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi> oppoſed themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Popes ſupremacie, and the worſhipping of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. <hi>Zon. tom.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 84.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Betweene the yeares 650. and 700.</head>
               <p>In <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>AIdan.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Finian.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Coleman,</hi> Three Scottiſh Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops. Alſo,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cutbertus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iurummanus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cedda.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> 
                  <hi>Wilfridus,</hi> of whom it is teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, that they gaue themſelues wholly to the preaching of the word, and followed that life which they preached, giuing good example to others; that they abhorred the papall pompe, and had many bitter controuerſies with the Court of <hi>Rome, Bed. lib.</hi> 2.23. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 4 <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>Martyrol. p.</hi> 110.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About the yeare 681. and in the 12. yeare of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Pagonatus,</hi> a generall Counſell was held at <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> where was diſanulled the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> concerning prohibition of Marriage to men in ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all offices, as alſo it was ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that the Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> ſhould bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall in authority with the Pope of <hi>Rome. Sext. Synod. Can.</hi> 13. Alſo it was forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to make the holy Ghoſt in likeneſſe of a Doue. <hi>Caxanc. in can.</hi> 82.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:20231:22"/>
               <p>In <hi>Portugall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Councell of <hi>Braca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> there held about this time, the Cup was appointed to bee miniſtred to the Laietie, as well as the Bread in the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Sacrament, againſt the practiſe of ſome who then vſed to dip the Bread, and ſo to giue it, which was one beginning of the halfe Communion. <hi>Concil. Bracaz.</hi> 3.1.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Betweene the yeares 600. and 650.</head>
               <p>In <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>MEllitus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Brockmaile.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>1100. Monkes of <hi>Bangor</hi> (not Monkes after the Popiſh or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but liuing by the ſweat of their browes, and labour of their owne hands) who were miſerably ſlaine, becauſe they withſtood the proceedings of <hi>Auſtin</hi> the Monke, who from the Pope was ſent ouer into <hi>England. Polychus,</hi> 20. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrol. p.</hi> 107.</p>
               <p>In <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Serenus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Marſils</hi> in <hi>France</hi> about this time op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the popiſh bringing in of <hi>Images</hi> into the Churches, and brake downe all the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages that that were ſet vp in his Dioceſſe, <hi>Alphonſ. v. Imago.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Greece.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The whole Greeke Church complained at <hi>Phocas,</hi> when firſt he gaue the Supremacie to <hi>Boniface. Plat. Bonif.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregorie</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> no leſſe conteſting againſt that Supremacie, taxing the deſire thereof as a Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of Antichriſt, <hi>Greg. Epiſt.</hi> 32.34.38, 39.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:20231:22"/>
               <p>Thus haue we traced the foot-ſteps of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Church 400. yeares and vpward before the Conqueſt of <hi>England</hi> by <hi>William</hi> Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> a thouſand yeares before <hi>Luthers</hi> time, or the daies of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight; and haue found our Religion profeſſed and maintained by diuers perſons, and in ſundrie places, not only here in <hi>England,</hi> but alſo in moſt parts of Chriſtendome, euen to the time when Poperie began to ſhew it ſelfe in her colours in the daies of <hi>Boniface</hi> the 3. of that name Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Phocas</hi> the Emperour.<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.7.</note> At what time as that myſterie of iniquitie, which began to worke in the Apoſtles dayes, did gather head, and diſplay it ſelfe; how eaſie it will bee for vs to deriue the ſucceſſion hereof from an higher diſcent, and to ſhew the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance thereof from the Apoſtles time, ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after be made manifeſt. In the meane while, we will for a while looke backe vnto our pope-Catholike Aduerſaries, and finde out their ſtarting holes, by examining what they obiect or can except againſt the Catalogue before recited, and ſee what colour they haue to ſet vpon their falſe ſuggeſtion which they buzze into the eares of their proſelites, <hi>that our Religion was not heard of before</hi> Luthers <hi>time,</hi> when we haue ſuch a cloude of Witneſſes of our ſide, as already hath beene produced.</p>
               <p>Their firſt cauill is againſt the ſmalneſſe of the number;<note place="margin">Genebrard. Chr. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Admit</hi> (ſay they) <hi>that there haue beene in the daies of old, ſome that haue leaned to diuers of theſe he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall propoſitions of the Proteſtants, and haue oppoſed themſelues againſt the doctrine of the Romiſh Church,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Briſt. praefat. in moti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>(as there hath beene ſcarce any peece or Article of the Roman
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20231:23"/> faith, but by one or other, firſt or laſt, it hath beene called in queſtion,)</hi> yet (as <hi>Andrew</hi> ſaid of the fiue Barly Loaues and two ſmall Fiſhes, which were to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided among fiue thouſand hungry people,<note place="margin">Iohn 6.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.9. <hi>What are theſe among ſo many?</hi> ſo ſay they? <hi>What are theſe few?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bellarm. lib. <hi>4.</hi> de Eccleſ. c. <hi>8.</hi> Rhem. in Act. <hi>11</hi> ſs. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>this little handfull of Proteſtants in regard of whole Countries Kingdomes, and Nations throughout all the world, who haue embraced the Catholike faith of the Church of Rome, and adhaered to that ſea? or how can ſo ſmall a number make a viſible Church?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this we anſwer, 1. That number or multitude is no true marke or note of a Church; for if Truth ſhould be meaſured by the opinion or practiſe of the multitude; Then <hi>Ieſabels</hi> Church ſhould bee better then the Church of which <hi>Elias</hi> was,<note place="margin">1 King. 18.19.</note> for <hi>Baals</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets were 450. fed at <hi>Ieſabels</hi> Table, when as <hi>Elias</hi> (as farre as hee could ſee) was left himſelfe alone, Then ſhould the Pagan religion bee better then that in <hi>Iſrael</hi> which was but an handfull in regard of the reſt of the world;<note place="margin">Pſal. 76.1.2. Pſal. 147.19.20.</note> Then ſhould Turkiſme bee better then the Chriſtian religion, for that at this day hath greater number that follow it then this. And ſo the Turke ſhould be better then the Pope, Mahume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme more to be commended then Poperie, becauſe the ones Dominion is larger in extent then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that hath more Proſelites then this: But our Bleſſed Sauiour himſelfe preuenteth that obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, when he calleth his flocke, <hi>Puſillum gregem, A little flocke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 12.31. Math. 7.13.</note> Luk. 12.13. and againe telleth vs. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.13. <hi>that wide is the gate and broad thei way that leadeth to deſtruction, and many there bee which goe in thereat, but ſtraight is the gate, and narrow the way which leadeth
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20231:23"/> vnto life, and few there bee that finde it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It is no wonder that in theſe times of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church of Chriſt by the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> the number of true profeſſors was ſo ſmall; for theſe were the daies and times,<note place="margin">Reuel. 12.5.6.</note> 
                  <hi>When this woman fled into the wilderneſſe,</hi> when the greateſt part of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an world, both <hi>ſmall and great, rich and poore,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 13.16, 17.</note> 
                  <hi>bond and free, were compelled to receaue the marke of the Beaſt, and no man could buy or ſell, ſaue hee that had the marke or the name of the beaſt, or the number of his name;</hi> By rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof the number of this faithfull flocke of Chriſt was much diminiſhed and obſcured; which is the cauſe why the profeſſors of our Religion in thoſe times, being driuen from place to place, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by Antichriſtian tyrannie; Their names, the places of their abode, and other circumſtances, whereby their memories ſhould haue beene preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, could not ſo eaſily be made knowne vnto vs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As the true Church may ſometimes bee more ſecret and hidden, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reduced to a very ſmall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as already hath beene declared, ſo that number, be it neuer ſo ſmall, that company be they neuer ſo few (profeſſing the Truth aright, and hauing the right markes of the Church) may be a true Church, <hi>Where two or three</hi> (ſaith our bleſſed Sauiour) <hi>are ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thered together in my name,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 18.26.</note> 
                  <hi>there am I in the middeſt of them. Mat.</hi> 18.20. Whereupon <hi>Tertullian</hi> inferreth,<note place="margin">Tertul. exhort. ad Caſtital. Auguſtin. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nar in <hi>pſal. 28</hi> Durand. lib. <hi>6.72.</hi> v. <hi>25.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Where three are that ſincerely profeſſe the truth, there is a Church;</hi> And <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Church ſometimes was only in the houſe of</hi> Noah, <hi>ſometimes in Abrahams family only, ſometimes in Lot and his houſe.</hi> And the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts themſelues doe acknowledge, that at the time of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20231:24"/> our Sauiours Paſſion the true <hi>Faith</hi> remayned onely in the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Neither haue I (in the Catologue before reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) ſet downe all that either liued or are recorded in the ſeuerall Ages aboue mentioned, but onely a few in ſtead of many; by which few it may bee eaſily ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered that there were many more of them, for ſuch Learned, ſuch eminent men, when they ſhew foorth themſelues, could not want partakers, howſoeuer the oppreſſion and Tyrannie of the aduerſe partie did keepe them vnder. Neither are there ſo few who haue already beene named, if wee rightly caſt the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; In ſome of theſe Centuries and halfe Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries (I confeſſe) there appeare more, in ſome leſſe, as the cloud of Popiſh ignorance or perſecution did thicken or leſſen; as ſometimes amounting to hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, at other times to thouſands, as may appeare by that which already hath been alledged. And this (if wee had no more witneſſes to preduce) were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for anſwer vnto their demand, who require vs to ſhew any that profeſſed our Religion before the dayes of <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> and to ſtop the mouthes of our Popiſh aduerſaries, who thus vauntingly inſult ouer vs,<note place="margin">Rhem. in Rom. <hi>11.4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>That they will not put the Proteſtants to proue, that there were ſeauen thouſand of their Sect before their new Elias,</hi> Luther <hi>began; But let them proue</hi> (ſay they) <hi>that there were ſeauen, or any one, either then, or before then, in any Age, that was in all points of his beliefe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>2</label> And theſe laſt wordes of the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> are a branch of another Obiection, which the Papiſts frame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our former Catologue.<note place="margin">Gregor. de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenc. Com. theol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om. <hi>3.</hi> d. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> And that is this, <hi>How can you prooue</hi> (ſay they) <hi>that thoſe parties whom you
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20231:24"/> claime to bee yours</hi> (ſuch as in the former Catalogue were mentioned) <hi>held the ſame Religion which you now doe, or if in ſome things they may ſeeme to accord with you, yet that in all points, they were of your beliefe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer: 1. <hi>That</hi> it is not requiſite that to proue them to profeſſe the ſame Religion together with vs, wee muſt proue them in all points to haue beene of our Beliefe, or that the leaſt difference in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion ſhould make a difference in Religion, for what Church euer was there, wherein all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof did fully conſent in euery point without any ſhew of difference? Surely, not the <hi>Pope Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church;</hi> for doe all that profeſſe themſelues members of that Church agree in euery point profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and maintained by that Church?<note place="margin">Concil. Trident. <hi>Watſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Quodl.</note> What then meane thoſe great Differences betweene the <hi>Scotiſts</hi> and <hi>Thomiſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See D. <hi>White</hi> his way to the true Church.</note> betweene the <hi>Dominicans</hi> and <hi>Franciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans,</hi> betweene the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Ieſuites;</hi> yea, betweene their beſt and moſt relied vpon Diuines? Yea what point of their Religion is there (wherein they and wee doe differ) which hath not beene contradicted by one or other of their owne Religion? Neither could the pureſt Churches in the primitiue Times claime freedome in all her members, from all diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in opinion, as hereafter ſhall bee manifeſted. Now then, if among thoſe whom in the Catalogue aboue mentioned I haue recorded, (to haue beene of our ſide) there be not found in euery point a joynt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion and full conſent, ſhall they therefore be deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to haue beene of our Religion? By the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, many of the ancient Fathers ſhould not be of the Communion of Saints or Catholike congregation,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20231:25"/> ſeeing that they likewiſe had their differences, and they that were moſt Orthodoxe amended the others errours. This therefore, can no whit preiudice our Cauſe, though all aboue mentioned did not in all and euery point of our Religion maintaine the ſame that we doe; for thus a learned Diuine of theirs doth acknowledge,<note place="margin">Luc, Pin. theſſ. vadem. theſ. <hi>83</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>That the vnitie of the Church conſiſteth in this, that the members thereof beleeue the ſame thinges, vſe the ſame worſhip of God, and receiue the ſame Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That they and wee hold the ſame Religion, we proue by the Teſtimonie of our Aduerſaries them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.<note place="margin">Campian. rat. <hi>10.</hi> Cochlae. hiſt. Huſſ. lib. <hi>1.</hi> &amp; <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Campian</hi> calleth <hi>Iohn Huſſe</hi> and <hi>Wichlief,</hi> the fore-runners of our Faith. <hi>Cochleus</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Iohn Huſſe</hi> tooke his Doctrine from the <hi>Wichleuiſts.</hi> And <hi>Aeneas Syluius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aene. Syl. hiſt. Bohem. c. <hi>35.</hi> Bellar. in Praf. generall Contr.</note> that the <hi>Wichleis</hi> did embrace the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the <hi>Waldenſes.</hi> And <hi>Bellarmine</hi> joyneth toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as profeſſors of the ſame Religion, the <hi>Berenga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, Petrobruſians, Albigenſes, Waldenſes, Wichliuiſts, Huſsits, Lutherans, Zuinglians, Caluiniſts, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. We proue them and vs to accord for ſubſtance in one and the ſame Religion, by comparing our Doctrine and practiſe now, with that of theirs in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times; The which concordance (to auoyd pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixitie) ſhall be manifeſted in theſe particulars.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> About the Scriptures.</head>
               <p>VVEe make them the rule &amp; tryall of our Faith, &amp; hold the ſufficiencie therof vnto ſaluation. <hi>Artic.</hi> 6. <hi>Synod. Lond. &amp; Homil.</hi> 10. So doth the <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:20231:25"/> confeſſion. <hi>Artic.</hi> 1. So <hi>Iohn Huſſe</hi> and the <hi>Bohemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Proteſtants. <hi>Iob. Huſſ. de abomin. Sacerd. &amp; Monach. pag.</hi> 84. So <hi>Iohn Wichlief, Artic.</hi> 6. collected out of his Sermons, <hi>Martyrol. pag.</hi> 396. So the <hi>Waldenſes, Artic.</hi> 1. <hi>vide hiſt. Waldenſ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What Bookes wee eſteeme Canonicall, and what <hi>Apochypha, Artic.</hi> 6. <hi>Synod. Lond.</hi> The ſame doe the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtan</hi> confeſſe. <hi>Artic.</hi> 2. obiects againſt them in the <hi>Trent</hi> Counſell, the <hi>French, Artic. Gal. confeſſ.</hi> 9. So the <hi>Belgicks, Artic.</hi> 41. <hi>Belgic. Confeſſ.</hi> So the <hi>Walden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Artic.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What wee hold for the tranſlation of them, and hauing them in the vulgar Tongue. <hi>Hom.</hi> 9. The ſame <hi>Weſelus Groningenſis. patet ex Nontemag.</hi> The <hi>Lollards, ſubregno henric.</hi> 5. <hi>Martyrol. p.</hi> 69. The <hi>Waldenſes, Art.</hi> 10. <hi>Arnulphus, ex opere tripart.</hi> King <hi>Alphred, Martyrol. pag.</hi> 1115. The <hi>French</hi> men aboue 200. yeares ſince, <hi>Praefat. in teſtum. Rheon. ſſ.</hi> 4. <hi>Confeſſ. Heluet. Art.</hi> 4. <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem. c.</hi> 1. <hi>Belgic. Art.</hi> 7. <hi>Saxon. Art.</hi> 1. <hi>Suerim. Artic.</hi> 1.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>About the Sacraments.</head>
               <p>AS wee hold that they are effectuall Seales and pledges, &amp;c. <hi>Artic.</hi> 25. <hi>Synod. Lond.</hi> So <hi>Magdeburg. Eccl. cent.</hi> 12. <hi>Auguſt. artic.</hi> 13. <hi>Heluet. artic.</hi> 29. <hi>Iohn Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chleif in Trialog. Waldenſ. art.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>As wee deny the Sacraments of themſelues to haue power to conferre Grace. <hi>Synod. Lond. artic.</hi> 26. <hi>Homil.</hi> 15. So <hi>Hierome Schuff. coram Archiep. Treuir. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherano</hi> and the <hi>Bohemtan</hi> Miniſters, <hi>Prucer.</hi> 5. <hi>Walden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Artic.</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>As wee acknowledge but two Sacraments, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20231:26"/> &amp; the Supper of the Lord. <hi>Catecluf. Angl. &amp; Art.</hi> 25. So <hi>Confeſſ. Heluet. artic.</hi> 20. <hi>Baſil. artic.</hi> 5. <hi>Belg. art.</hi> 33. <hi>Saxon. artic.</hi> 12. So <hi>Weſelus Groningenſ Iohan. Monterger, Anton. Nancinel. vt ſupra. Waldenſes, artic.</hi> 11.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>About Baptiſme.</head>
               <p>AS wee deny <hi>Baptiſme</hi> of it ſelfe to waſh away all Sinne, or to conferre Grace <hi>ex opere operato. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic.</hi> 27. So <hi>Confeſſ. Heluet. artic.</hi> 21. <hi>Auguſtan, artic.</hi> 9. <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem</hi> 12. <hi>Wittemb. c.</hi> 10.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>About the Supper of the Lord.</head>
               <p>AS wee deny the reall preſence of CHRISTS very Bodie and Blood in that Sacrament. <hi>Synod. Lond. artic.</hi> 28. So <hi>Confeſſ. Heluet. art.</hi> 22. <hi>Bohem.</hi> 13. <hi>Picus Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randula, Iohn Huſſe, Wichleif,</hi> the <hi>Waldenſes, Aelfricus,</hi> and in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner all in our Catalogue before recorded.</p>
               <p>As we conteſt againſt the Maſſe. <hi>Homil.</hi> 15. So <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ. Heluet. artic.</hi> 11. <hi>Bohem. c.</hi> 6. <hi>Auguſtan. artic.</hi> 34. So <hi>Gerrhardus, Dulcinus, Arnulphus, vt ſupra.</hi> So the <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſes, artic.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>As wee maintaine the receiuing of the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in both kindes. <hi>Synod. Lond. artic.</hi> 30. So <hi>Confeſſ. Heluet. artic.</hi> 22. <hi>Saxon. act.</hi> 15. <hi>Iohn Huſſ. Caleſtini, ſub v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traque in Bohem. Waldenſes, Artic.</hi> 11.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>About the Church.</head>
               <p>AS wee hold the due adminiſtration of the Word and Sacraments, to bee the true markes of the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:20231:26"/> viſible Church. <hi>Synod. Lond. artic.</hi> 19. So <hi>Confeſſ. Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet. act.</hi> 14. <hi>Bohem. c.</hi> 8. <hi>Suen.</hi> 32.</p>
               <p>As wee deny the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to bee the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Church. <hi>Homil.</hi> 1. So <hi>Confeſſ. Auguſt. artic.</hi> 4. <hi>Arnolph. in concil. Rhem. Wichleif. Sygebert, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As wee deny the Churches authority to be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the Scriptures. <hi>Synod. Lond. artic.</hi> 20. ſo <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ. Heluet. artic.</hi> 4. <hi>Baſil. artic.</hi> 10. <hi>Bohem. c.</hi> 1. Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers in <hi>Suiden. Abbas vſpag. Gulielm. de Sanct. Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>About the Pope.</head>
               <p>AS wee denie the Popes Supremacie. <hi>Oath of allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance.</hi> ſo <hi>Confeſſ. Heluet. artic.</hi> 18. <hi>Bohem. c.</hi> 8. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtan. artic.</hi> 7. ſo <hi>Hierome Sauanorola; Thomas Rhedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſis, Wichleif, Gulielmus Ocham, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As we hold the Pope to be Antichriſt. <hi>King Iames Expoſ. of the Reuel.</hi> So the Councell in <hi>France</hi> vnder <hi>Hugh Capet.</hi> So <hi>Antoninus Marcidellis, Mathias Pariſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſis, Marſilius Patauinus, Rochetailada,</hi> and in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner all in the Catalogue before mentioned.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Juſtification.</head>
               <p>AS wee hold that we are juſtified by Faith, and not by Workes. <hi>Synod. Lond. artic.</hi> 11. So <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ. Heluet.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 16. <hi>Auguſtan. artic.</hi> 6. <hi>Bohem. c.</hi> 7. <hi>Weſelus Groning. Pieus Mirandula, Bernard, Arnulphus, &amp;c. vt ſupra.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:20231:27"/>
               <head>About Prieſts Marriage.</head>
               <p>AS wee hold it lawfull by the word of God for Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, &amp;c. to Marrie. <hi>Artic.</hi> 32. So <hi>Confeſſ. Heluet. artic.</hi> 37. <hi>Bohem. c.</hi> 9. <hi>Wittemb. c.</hi> 21. <hi>VValdenſes. artic.</hi> 9.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>About Purgatorie.</head>
               <p>AS wee reiect the opinion of Poperie as fond and ridiculous. <hi>Synod. Lond. artic.</hi> 22. So <hi>Confeſſ. Helu. c.</hi> 26. <hi>Auguſt. artic.</hi> 11. ſo the <hi>Waldenſes, artic.</hi> 3. ſo <hi>Iohn Huſſe, Wichleif,</hi> and the moſt part of the aboue named, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>About the Ciuill Magiſtrate.</head>
               <p>AS wee hold that Kings and Princes haue the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt power in their Kingdomes, both in cauſes Ciuill and Eccleſiaſticall. <hi>Synod. Lond. art.</hi> 37. ſo <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ. Heluet. artic.</hi> 26. <hi>Bohem. c.</hi> 16. <hi>Auguſtan. artic.</hi> 16. ſo <hi>Henry</hi> the 5. Emperour, <hi>Frederich, Barbaroſia, Taulerus Pleſiano, Ludo,</hi> and the moſt of the reſt aboue named.</p>
               <p>I might goe on in the compariſon through euery point of Doctrine in our Churches, and ſhew the conſent of theſe likewiſe in the particulars together with vs; But for auoyding of prolixitie, I referre the Reader to the examination hereof, in the denota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their particular opinions, as they are ſet downe in order in the Catalogue.</p>
               <p>And here by the way wee will meer with another Objection of theirs which is this; <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>3</label> 
                  <hi>What doe you talke</hi> (ſay they) <hi>of Vnitie and Conſent in your</hi> Proteſtant <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches? you cannot tell whom you follow, nor who are with
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:20231:27"/> you; The</hi> Lutherans <hi>are againſt the</hi> Zuinglians, <hi>theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the</hi> Caluiniſts; <hi>The</hi> Geneua <hi>and other reformed Churches, differ in many points from the</hi> Engliſh; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any in the Catalogue before mentioned, were <hi>Lutherans,</hi> they were none of yours; If they were <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiniſts,</hi> they were none of yours? And therefore, <hi>how can you ſhew your Religion in former times.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer. 1. It is not ſtrange to ſee difference in ſome circumſtances betweene thoſe that profeſſe one and the ſame Religion. St. <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifieth of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> (euen then when it was at the beſt) <hi>That there were therein who cauſed diuiſions and diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, contrary to the Doctrine which they had receiued.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 16.17.</note> And of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> hee ſaith, <hi>There was among them en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uying, ſtrife and contention, ſome held of</hi> Paul,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.3. Act. 15.39. Gal. 2.11.</note> 
                  <hi>ſome of</hi> Apollos, <hi>ſome of</hi> Cephas. So <hi>Paul</hi> &amp; <hi>Barrabas,</hi> yea <hi>Paul</hi> &amp; <hi>Peter</hi> had their differences. So <hi>Polycrates</hi> and <hi>Victor, Cyprian</hi> and <hi>Cornelius, Cyrill</hi> &amp; <hi>Theodoret, Hierome</hi> and <hi>Ruffinus. Nazianzen</hi> and the Councell of <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> had not onely their differences, but alſo bitter op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions; yet all agreeing in the ſubſtance of Faith, &amp; reputed members of the ſame Catholike Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Wee anſwer, The defects and corruptions of Churches muſt be diſtinguiſhed; and they bee either in Doctrine or in manners; Againe, corruptions in Doctrine muſt further bee diſtinguiſhed, ſome of them are errours indeed, but beſides the foundation, ſome directly againſt the foundation, and theſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerturne all Religion, whereas the former doe not. As are theſe defects and corruptions in Churches, ſo are their differences, ſome about Ceremonies, ſome about ſubſtance. Now although the Churches of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:20231:28"/> 
                  <hi>Geneua, Heluetia, Belgia,</hi> &amp;c. differ from vs in ſome points of Ceremonies and Circumſtances, yet looke we to the ſubſtance of Faith and Doctrine which wee and they profeſſe, there is no difference at all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene vs; Indeed the maine difference is betweene vs and them, about the point of <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</hi> But marke in what manner, we all ioyntly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in the ſubſtance of the <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> confeſſing on each ſide that there muſt bee the Preaching of the Word, Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the inſtitution, and the vſe of the power of the Keyes, in Admonitions, Suſpenſions, Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications; The difference betweene vs is onely tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the perſons, and the manner of putting this Diſcipline in execution; And therefore notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this by difference, wee and they are of one and the ſame Religion, as may likewiſe appeare by the Harmonie of <hi>Confeſſions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. As concerning thoſe Churches, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly are called the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Churches; though their <hi>Auguſtan</hi> Confeſſion hath not ſatisfied the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of other of the reformed Churches, and ſome of the more rigid among them,<note place="margin">Admonition of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in the <hi>Parler.</hi>
                  </note> hate vs as bad as <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> yet we and they are of one Church; for we haue the ſame enemies in matters of Religion, and doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like confeſſe the Diuinitie, The office of the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, the doctrine of Faith, of good Workes, of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and in opinion about the Word, the Church, the Magiſtrate, are of one iudgement. They differ indeed from vs in the matter of rhe Sacrament, and therein are in a groſſe errour. But that difference betweene them and vs, doth not take away wholly
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:20231:28"/> the Analigie of Faith and Doctrine betweene vs; for that there is a true and reall receiuing of the Bodie and Blood of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the Lords Supper, we all agree. And we joyntly confeſſe, that Chriſt is there preſent ſo farre forth, that he doth truly feed vs with his very Body and Blood to Eternall life; all the controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie lyeth in the manner of receiuing, wee acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging a Spirituall receiuing, which is by the hand of Faith; They adding thereto the Corporall, whereby they imagine themſelues to receiue Chriſt with the hand and mouth of the Bodie. And though to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this their opinion they be conſtrained to turne the aſcenſion of Chriſt into a diſparition, whereby his Body being viſible becommeth inuiſible; yet in the maine points wee agree, that <hi>hee entred</hi> into his Kingdome in our name for vs; that we are gouerned and preſerued by his power &amp; might, and that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer good thing we haue or do, proceedeth wholly from the grace of his Spirit; wee pittie their errours, and leaue their perſons vnto God. Againe <hi>Popiſh</hi> Tranſubſtantiation, and <hi>Lutheran</hi> Conſubſtantiation are both, we confeſſe, againſt the truth of the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of Chriſt, yet with great difference. Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation is flat againſt an Article of Faith; for if Chriſt his body be made of Bread, and his blood of Wine, (which muſt needs be, if there be a conuerſion of the one into the other) then was hee not borne of the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> for it cannot bee both made of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers bread, and alſo of the ſubſtance of the Virgin. Againe, it wholly aboliſheth the outward Signe, and the analogie betweene the ſigne and the thing ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and ſo ouerturneth the Sacrament. But Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:20231:29"/> doth not ſo,<note place="margin">Q.</note> neither doth it ouerthrow the ſubſtance of any Article of Religion, but onely a maine point of Philoſophie, which is, <hi>That a Body doth occupie onely one place at one time.</hi> Therefore how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer in this point there bee a great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the <hi>Lutherans</hi> and vs, yet we may bee both of one Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>4</label> I come now to the 4. cauill and Obiection which our Aduerſaries the <hi>Papiſts</hi> obiect againſt our former Catalogue of <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Popiſh diſc. of Faith <hi>ſs.</hi> 57</note> 
                  <hi>Admit</hi> (ſay they) <hi>that in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages you can finde ſome that were your anceſtors, and the forerunners of your Faith;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Stapleton. de Iuſtif. lib. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>7</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>yet what manner of perſons were they? Such as were notorious Hereticks, men branded with the marke of groſſe and damnable Doctrines,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Campia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. rat. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and helliſh liues, Reprobates, condemned by Popes and generall Councels, yea the very dregs, and the bellowes, and the Iewell of hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this we anſwer. 1. That it is no new thing for thoſe, who are moſt blameleſſe to be ſlaundered with many falſe and vniuſt calumniations; <hi>Bleſſed are yee</hi> (ſaith our bleſſed Sauiour) <hi>when men ſhall reuile you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 5.11.12</note> 
                  <hi>and perſecute you, &amp; ſhal ſay all manner of euill againſt you falſly for my ſake; Reioyce &amp; be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in heauen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 2.13. &amp; 16 20. &amp; 17.7. 2. Cor. 12.16.</note> 
                  <hi>for ſo proſecuted they the Prophets which were before you.</hi> As were the Prophets ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Apoſtles, at more times and in more places then one, charged with many accuſations, which yet in truth were but meere calumniations,<note place="margin">Plinius.</note> ſo the <hi>Iewes</hi> (when the viſible Church of God was onely among them) were ſlandered as worſhippers of Hogs,<note place="margin">Cornel. Tacit.</note> and Aſſes, and contemners of all Religion; So the olde Chriſtians in the Primitiue Church, were ſlandered
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:20231:29"/> to vſe inceſtuous companie each with other like <hi>Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dipus,</hi> and to eate mans fleſh at the banquet of <hi>Thyeſtes;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Euſeb. Eccleſ. hiſt. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> Socrat. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>2</hi> Euſeb. lib. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>6</hi> Sozom. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>25</hi> Idem lib. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>28</hi>
                  </note> So <hi>Athanaſius, Narciſſus, Cyrill, Chryſoſtome,</hi> and which elſe of the ancienteſt worthies of the Church, haue been free from ſlanders and ſiniſter imputations? No maruell then if theſe, who in their ſeuerall times did ſeperate themſelues from the common corruptions of the Times, and withſtood the errours of thoſe lines, doe taſte of the malignant aſperſion in thoſe times.</p>
               <p>Secondly, wee are not ſo much to regard what the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and their Councels haue thought and pronounced againſt theſe our Ancients, for they were parties partially affected againſt theſe their oppoſits, and it is no rare thing with that Synagogue, to damne thoſe to the pit of hell, who any wayes croſſe their proceedings; Neither doe wee beleeue that all they are or were Hereticks, whom the Papiſts call he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes; for whatſoeuer doth withſtand their Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchie, they account hereſie. But our Apologie in that behalfe is that of the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 24.14.</note> 
                  <hi>After the way which they call hereſie, ſo worſhip wee the God of our Fathers.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rob. Groſthead <hi>B. of</hi> Lincoln. vt citatur in Wichleif trialog.</note> And if that deſcription of Hereſie may goe for currant, which was deliuered by a Reuerend and learned Prelate in this Land, almoſt foure hundred yeares agone,<note place="margin">Haereſis Graece, electio Latine eſt ſententia hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano ſenſu ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu, ſcripturae ſacrae contrar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> palam docta, pertinaciter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſu.</note> 
                  <hi>That Hereſie is an opinion hatch'd in mans owne braine, contrary to holy Scripture, openly maintained, and ſtifly defended;</hi> then can they by no meanes brand either vs or theſe our predeceſſors, with the name of Hereticks, who neither hold any opinions grounded vpon our owne fancies, neither openly maintained or ſtoutly ſtand to any errours whereof they iuſtly can
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:20231:30"/> conuict vs, but that wee and they are truely ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxe and right Catholikes, who teach and maintaine nothing, but that whereof we haue euident warrant out of the Word of God.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, what is that which they can obiect againſt any of thoſe who are mentioned in our former Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue? Is it concerning our Faith or Life, or both? Let vs looke to the Triall of the particulars, and I doubt not, but all their ſuggeſtions will proue lyes, and meere ſlanders, as may appeare if we doe take a view of the particulars.</p>
               <p>And here. 1. Wee will begin at <hi>Luther,</hi> becauſe their ſpight is moſt againſt him, as being a principall oppoſite of theirs, and vpon whom they would fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the beginning of our cauſe. And let vs heare what they can ſay againſt <hi>Luther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Popiſh Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Faith. <hi>ſſ.</hi> 57.</note>
                  <hi>Martin Luther</hi> (ſay they) <hi>was an Apoſtate Frier, a man knowne by his writings, words, deeds, and death, to haue beene a notorious euill liuer.</hi> That <hi>Luther</hi> was ſomtimes a Frier, wee grant, and that afterwards through the mercy of God, hee obtaining a more cleare know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth, renounced their profeſſion we doe not deny; But what Apoſtaſie was this in him? or how can it more diſparage him,<note place="margin">Act. 22.3. &amp; 23.6. &amp; 9.1, 2, 3, 6, 18, 19. D. <hi>White</hi> his way to the true Church.</note> then it did the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who at the firſt was a <hi>Phariſie,</hi> and after that, being better illightned by God, renounced the profeſſion Phariſaicall, and became an Apoſtle, both thoſe former profeſſions being meere hypocriſie, ſaue that this of the Frier is of the deeper tincture.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Stapleton. diſc. p. <hi>159.</hi>
                  </note>And what haue they to ſay againſt his Writings? <hi>Forſooth they were vnſauourie, raſh, petulant, vnſound, and altogether heriticall.</hi> Soone ſaid, but not ſo ſoone pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:20231:30"/> for it doth ſo appeare by their confutation of the ſame? let them make that appeare, and then wee will credit them; In the meane ſpace, howſoeuer we ſtand not in defence of all, either matter or manner of his writings, neither indeed doe wee build vpon him, we will rather giue credit to ſome leſſe partiall, but more iuditious euen among the Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, who giue other manner of teſtimonie concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Luthers</hi> writings;<note place="margin">Q. Eraſm: ad Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din: Mogunt.</note> for thus <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſpeaketh of them; <hi>It is obſerued for a truth, that theſe men</hi> (meaning the Papiſts) <hi>condemne many things in</hi> Luthers <hi>bookes, which in</hi> Auguſtine <hi>and</hi> Bernard <hi>are read for godly and good diuinitie;</hi> And he addeth, <hi>That hee ſeeth this, the beſt men are leaſt offended at his writings.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſiand. Hiſt. Eccleſ. cent. <hi>16.</hi> p. <hi>837.</hi>
                  </note> So <hi>Andreas Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> in the company of diuers obſerued and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, <hi>that there was more diuinitie in one page of</hi> Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>then ſometimes in a whole booke of ſome Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And what can they obiect againſt his life? did he forſake his Monaſterie and giue himſelfe to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, following him, and doing homage vnto him, that all things might proſper according to his minde; as did <hi>Silueſter</hi> the ſecond?<note place="margin">Platin. in Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> did hee robbe Churches, and murther his Predeceſſors, as did Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the ſeauenth;<note place="margin">Baron ann <hi>985</hi> n. <hi>1.</hi> Onu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> did he commit inceſt with his owne Daughter, as did Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixth? did he caſt the Sacrament into the fire, as did Pope <hi>Hildebrand?</hi> did he keepe a beuie of whores,<note place="margin">Benno Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalis. Luitprand. lib. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>6. &amp;. 7.</hi>
                  </note> turne the Church into a Stewes, drinke healths to the deuill, reuell vp and downe the ſtreetes in armour, and ſet mens houſes on fire, as Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> the 12. did? No ſurely: Not any ſhew in <hi>Luthers</hi> life of any of theſe or ſuch like offences, yea, <hi>Eraſmus</hi> (one who
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:20231:31"/> was familiar with him) in a certaine Epiſtle to Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>Wolſie</hi> giueth teſtimonie of him,<note place="margin">Eraſm. Epiſt. ad Cardinal. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rac.</note> 
                  <hi>that his life was approued with great conſent of all men, And this</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is no ſmall honour to him, that the integritie of his manners is ſo great, that his very enemies can finde nothing which they may Calumniate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pontac. Campian. Onupb. in Ioh. <hi>8</hi>
                  </note>What deedes then hath he done, for which they ſhould finde ſuch fault with his life? <hi>Forſooth he mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried a Nunne, hee lay with Bora;</hi> hee lay with her; But firſt he married her; hee had not his <hi>Marozias, Reyne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras, Theodoraes, Stephanaes,</hi> to be his bedfellowes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any care or veile of marriage;<note place="margin">Baron. in ann. <hi>928. 912.</hi>
                  </note> But <hi>hee was a Frier, ſhee a Nunne, both which had vowed not to marrie:</hi> But who tied them to thoſe vowes? or what vow of man can diſanull the lawfulneſſe of Gods owne ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1 Cor. 7.9.</hi> Rubrio. qui non habit vxorem habent Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binam.</note> Whether, <hi>is it not better to marrie then to burne?</hi> Whether is it not more Clerke-like to haue a wife of his owne, then (which is common among them) to haue diſpenſation to keepe a Concubine? It is a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led caſe in their Schooles, and vſuall in the popiſh practiſe in this kinde to diſpenſe with vowes: was this <hi>Martin Luthers</hi> fault, that hee married without their papall diſpenſations?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Leonic. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>al. p. <hi>246.</hi>
                  </note>But what is it which our Papiſts haue to ſay of the death of this worthy man? <hi>An horrible miracle</hi> (ſaith one of them) <hi>and ſuch as before was neuer heard of, that God ſhewed in the ſoule death of</hi> Martin Luther, <hi>damned in body and ſoule: when</hi> Martin Luther <hi>fell into his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, Hee deſired the body of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt to bee giuen vnto him, which hauing receaued, hee died ſoone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: Being dead, and his body laid in the graue, on the ſudden ſuch a tumult and terror aroſe, as if the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:20231:31"/> of the earth had been ſhaken; the next night after was heard a noiſe and cracking about</hi> Luthers <hi>Tombe much lowder then before, which waked all that were in the Citie out of their ſleepe, trembling, and almoſt dead for feare, wherefore in the morning opening the Sepulchre where</hi> Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>deteſtable bodie was laid, they found neither bodie nor bones, nor clothes, but a ſtinke of Brimſtone comming out of the graue, had well-nigh killed all the ſtanders by.</hi> An horrible and dreadfull example indeed, if it were true: But when I pray was this report raiſed? when was it written? ſurely long before <hi>Luthers</hi> death; And this merry conceite being diuulged abroad, &amp; ſuckt in greedily by the Papall faction, at length a coppie thereof came to <hi>Luthers</hi> hands,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>D. White</hi> his way to the true Church. <hi>p.</hi> 430.</note> to the which Libell he writ an Anſwer beginning in theſe words, <hi>I Martin Luther, by this mine hand writing confeſſe and teſtifie, that vpon the</hi> 21. <hi>of March I receaued this fiction concerning my death, as it was full of mallice &amp; madneſſe, and I read it with a glad minde and cheerfull countenance, &amp;c.</hi> What? my maſters the Papiſts, are you not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of theſe iuggling impoſtures? Are you growne ſo impudent, that you will not conceale your falſe Tales and forgeries, which you inuent againſt holy men of God, till they be dead, but publiſh them in Print in their liues time, that they themſelues (as <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> and <hi>Beza</hi> did) may conuince you of ſlaunder and of mallice?<note place="margin">Bez. Epiſt. ad ſtuckium.</note> No wonder then that you bluſh not to traduce <hi>Caluin, Iewell, King,</hi> and other worthy inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Gods glorie, when they are dead. But you will ſay, you haue a true relation of <hi>Luthers</hi> fearefull end, and that ſet forth after he was dead indeed; Let vs heare what it is; Marry this (ſay they) <hi>Martin Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:20231:32"/> going to bed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Coccl. vit Luth. Caluinaturciſm. p.</hi> 957. Defence of the Cenſ. <hi>p.</hi> 66</note> 
                  <hi>merry and drunken, was found the next morning dead in his bed, his body being blacke, and his tongue ſwelling forth as if hee had beene ſtrangled, which ſome thinke was done by the Deuill, ſome by his wife: And that as they bare him to Church to burie him, his body ſo ſmelt, that they were faine to throw it into a ditch, and goe their waies:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Thyrraus de Daemoniac. part. <hi>1.</hi> Theſ. <hi>99.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>And that a ſeruant of</hi> Luthers <hi>being in the Chamber when he died, opening a Caſement to take in the ayre, ſaw neere vnto him a great number of blacke ſpirits hopping and dancing wonderfull?</hi> But did they who relate this ſee it? were they then preſent? or vpon whoſe relation doe they deliuer it? Nay here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are altogether ſilent; Therefore let vs heare what they who were preſent with <hi>Luther</hi> at the time of his death, and ſaw him dying, and accompanied his body to the Funerall, bee rather belieued then theſe rayling lying Papiſts; And who were theſe? <hi>Albert</hi> Earle of <hi>Mansfield</hi> and other noble men,<note place="margin">Ioh. Sleidan. Com. lib. c. <hi>16.</hi> Hierom in Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler. Martyrol. p. <hi>789</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Iuſtus Ionas, Michael Coelius, Iohannes Auriſaber, Ambroſe</hi> his his childrens Schoolemaſter, and many more; And what teſtifie they of his manner of dying, euen this: <hi>That in the yeare of our Lord</hi> 1546. <hi>the</hi> 17. <hi>of Februarie, D.</hi> Martin Luther <hi>ſickened a little before ſupper of his accuſtomed maladie, to wit, the oppreſsion of humours in the crifice or opening of his stomacke; which ſickneſſe ſeaſoning vpon him, hee was had to bed, where hee reſted two houres, where his paines encreaſing, he called vp D.</hi> Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas <hi>and</hi> Ambroſe <hi>his childrens Schoole-maſter, and by their helpe remoued into an other Chamber; Into which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing newly entred,</hi> Albert <hi>Earle of</hi> Mansfield <hi>with diuers other came into his Chamber, with whom he learnedly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed; of our knowledge in the life to come, of the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:20231:32"/> labours in the</hi> Trent <hi>Counſell to ſuppreſſe the truth, of the care which euery good Chriſtian ſhould take to maintaine the truth; Giuing himſelfe many times to his priuate pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and ſoliloquies with God; And feeling his fatall houre to approch, he commended himſelfe to God with this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout prayer; Heauenly Father, who art God, and the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the God of all comfort, I giue thee thankes for that thou haſt reuealed thy Sonne Chriſt vnto me, in whom I haue beleeued, whom I haue profeſſed, loued, and preached; and whom the Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>and the reſt of the wicked perſecute and reproach; I beſeech thee, my Lord Ieſus Chriſt, receiue my poore ſoule,</hi> And, <hi>Heauenly father, though I bee taken out of this life, and ſhall lay downe this my body, yet I beleeue aſſuredly, that I ſhall remaine foreuer with thee, and that none ſhall bee able to plucke mee out of thine hands. And hauing ended this prayer, hee repeated the</hi> 16. <hi>verſe of the</hi> 3. <hi>chapter of the Goſpell by S.</hi> Iohn, <hi>and then the</hi> 20. <hi>verſe of the</hi> 68. <hi>Pſalme, and not long after this hee commended his ſoule into the hands of God two or three times ouer, with ſhew of much comfort, as a man falling aſleepe by little and little, he departed this life; the ſtanders by perceiuing no paine to vexe him;</hi> his Funerals were ſolemnly perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at <hi>Wittenberge,</hi> where by the appointment of the Prince Elector, hee was honourably buried in the tower Church, with great lamentation of many, <hi>Bugenhagius</hi> making the Funerall Sermon, and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancton</hi> the Oration. This was the end of that good man, whoſe memorie ſhall euer be precious in the Church of Chriſt, and flouriſh as the rod of <hi>Aaron</hi> laid vp in the Tabernacle. Thus much for the Popiſh exceptions againſt <hi>Luther.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20231:33"/>
               <p>The next whom they except againſt are <hi>Iohn Huffe</hi> and <hi>Hierome</hi> of <hi>Prage,</hi> the two famous Bohemian Martyrs, and learned profeſſors of our religion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And what is it which they can ſay againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>m <hi>Iohn Huſſe</hi> (ſay they) <hi>was a very Gooſe</hi> (ſo it pleaſeth them to deſcant vpon his name,<note place="margin">Stephen Paletz. Staniſlaus de Znoymar. Concil. Conſtan.</note> which in that tongue doth ſo ſignifie. <hi>Hierome of</hi> Prage <hi>a meere Sophiſter: both of them Arch heretickes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cochleus. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Hiſtor. Huſſit. p. <hi>88.</hi> Dico igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Iohannem Huſſe neque ſanctum, neque beatum haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſed impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um potius, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>turbulent and pernitious perſons, ambitiouſly deſiring vaine glorie, maintainers of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and deteſtable opinions. Cochleus</hi> thus writeth of them: <hi>I ſay therefore that</hi> Iohn Huſſe <hi>is neither to bee accounted holy nor bleſſed, but rather wicked and eternally wretched, inſomuch that at the day of Iudgement it ſhall be more eaſie, not only with the Infidell Pagans, Turkes, Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians, and Iewes, but alſo with the moſt ſinfull Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites, and the abominable Perſians, yea alſo with moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious</hi> Cain <hi>killer of his owne brother, with</hi> Thyeſtes <hi>kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of his owne mother, and the</hi> Leſtrigones, <hi>and other Anthropaphagi, which deuoure mans fleſh: yea more eaſie with thoſe infamous murtherers of Infants,</hi> Pharaoh <hi>and</hi> Herod, <hi>then it ſhall be with him, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Duraverba,</hi> A raſh and harſh ſentence, <hi>yet</hi> Michael <hi>the Archangell when he contended with the Deuill,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iude 9.10.</note> 
                  <hi>diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting about the Body of</hi> Moſes, <hi>durſt not bring againſt him a railing accuſation, but ſaid, The Lord rebuke thee, But theſe ſpeake euill of things they know not.</hi> They con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne theſe two worthy Diuines for Heretikes, their doctrine for hereſie, and burne them, damne them to hell, raile againſt their memorie, before they proue either them or their doctrine Hereticall.<note place="margin">Aenaeas Siluius. Antoninus. Laziardus.</note> True indeed it is, that <hi>Aeneas Siluius</hi> (knowne afterwards by the name of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the 2.) and <hi>Antoninu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:20231:33"/> 
                  <hi>Laziardus</hi> doe falſly father many erronious Articles vpon them, which they neuer maintained,<note place="margin">Recognitio ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis &amp; Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. Prag. Auguſt. <hi>30. 1414.</hi>
                  </note> neither came it into their heart to maintaine, as both them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues doe profeſſe, and the Citie of <hi>Prage</hi> witneſſe with them; And in the Councell of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides many falſe accuſations ſuggeſted againſt them, and their doctrine, their true opinions were conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as haereticall; But how were they proued ſo to be? how were they confuted? did not he plead his cauſe before the whole Councell? did hee not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to reuoke his opinions if by the word of God, it might be proued that he had erred? did they goe about by the Scriptures, and not rather by clamours, outrages, and reproaches to anſwer him? I appeale to the Acts of the Councell. Nay more, heare the teſtimonie of one who was deputed Inquiſitor to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into the doctrine of <hi>Iohn Huſſe</hi> by the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that is the Biſhop of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> Inquiſitor of hereſie in the Citie, and Dioceſſe of <hi>Prage,</hi> who by his Letters written, doth cleere him from any he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall poſition. The coppie of whoſe Letter is to this effect.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>WEE <hi>Nicholas</hi> by the grace of God,<note place="margin">Martyrolog. p. <hi>549.</hi>
                        </note> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> and Inquiſitor, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally deputed by the Apoſtolike Seat for hereſies, both of the Citie and Dioceſſe of <hi>Prage,</hi> by theſe preſents make it knowne to all men, that wee haue often com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muned and talked with that honourable man, Maſter <hi>Iohn Huſſe,</hi> Bachelor of Diuinitie of the famous
<pb facs="tcp:20231:34"/> Vniuerſitie of <hi>Prage,</hi> and haue had diuers and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Conferences with him, both of the Scriptures, and diuers other matters; And in all his ſayings, doings, and behauiour, wee haue proued and found him to be a faithfull, and a catholicke man, finding no manner of euill, ſiniſter, or by any meanes erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous doings in him: to this preſent we doe witneſſe and proteſt moreouer, how the ſaid <hi>Iohn Huſſe</hi> of late in the Cathedrall Church of <hi>Prage, &amp;c.</hi> hath ſet vp his Letters written both in the Latine and Bohemian tongue, containing ſententially in effect, that hee the aforeſaid <hi>Iohn Huſſe</hi> would appeare before the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Father <hi>Conrade</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Prage</hi> and all the Prelates and Clergie of the Kingdome of <hi>Boheme, &amp;c.</hi> and there be ready to ſatisfie euery man that ſhall require him to ſhew a reaſon of his faith and hope that he holdeth, and to ſee and heare all and euery one which could proue any obſtinacie of error or hereſie, lawfully againſt him, vnder paine to receiue the like puniſhment: alſo that he would be at the Councell of <hi>Conſtance</hi> now at hand, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the Prelates and holy Fathers, to declare and ſhew forth his innocencie: After the which Letters as is aforeſaid by the ſaid Maſter <hi>Iohn Huſſe,</hi> open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet vp. There did no man appeare before vs which would accuſe the ſaid <hi>Iohn Huſſe</hi> of any error or
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:20231:34"/> hereſie whatſoeuer. For euident witneſſe of all which thinges, wee haue commanded theſe preſent Letters to bee made, and confirmed the ſame with the ſetting to of our Seale.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Dated in</hi> Prague, <date>
                              <hi>30. of Auguſt,</hi> Anno Dom. <hi>1414.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>As for that aſperſion of Ambition or vaine glory,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh. Huſſ</hi> de Sacerd. &amp; Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nachor. abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. pag. <hi>84.</hi> Nam &amp; iſta ſcribens fateor quod nihil aliud me in illi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, niſi dilectio Domini Ieſu crucifixi, &amp;c.</note> which the Pope-Catholikes would faſten vpon this holy man, let vs heare his owne Apologie; <hi>In writing theſe thinges</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>I confeſſe that nothing elſe hath moued mee hereunto, but onely the loue of our Lord</hi> IESVS <hi>Crucified, whoſe prints and ſtripes (according to the meaſure of my weakneſſe and vileneſſe) I couet to beare in my ſelfe, beſeeching him ſo to aſsiſt mee with his Grace, that I may neuer ſeeke to glory in my ſelfe, or in any thing elſe, but onely in his Croſſe, and in the ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable ignominie of his Paſsion which hee ſuffered for mee. And therefore, I write and ſpeake theſe thinges, which I doubt not but will like all ſuch as vnfainedly loue the Lord</hi> IESVS CHRIST, <hi>and contrariwiſe will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like not a little all ſuch as bee of</hi> Antichriſt: <hi>Alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, I confeſſe before the moſt mercifull Lord</hi> IESVS CHRIST <hi>Crucified, that theſe thinges which I doe now write, and thoſe which I haue written before, neither I could haue written, nor knew how, nor durſt ſo to haue written, vnleſſe hee by his inward vnction had ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded mee: Neither yet doe I write theſe thinges, as of authoritie, to get mee a name, for</hi> (as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Hierome</hi> doe ſay) <hi>that is onely to bee giuen to the
<pb facs="tcp:20231:35"/> Scriptures, and writings of the Apoſtles, Euangeliſts, and Prophets, which doe abound in the fulneſſe of the Spirit of</hi> IESVS, <hi>and whatſoeuer is there ſaid is full of veritie and wholſome vtilitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As concerning the life and conuerſation both of <hi>Iohn Huſſe,</hi> and <hi>Hierome</hi> of <hi>Prague,</hi> which the Papiſts labour to traduce, let vs heare the teſtimonie, not of <hi>Plebians,</hi> but of the Nobles of <hi>Morauia,</hi> not a few, but 54. of them, written to the Councell of <hi>Conſtance</hi> in their defence. The Copie of it beginneth thus:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">Extat. Marty. vol. p. <hi>386.</hi> &amp; <hi>387.</hi>
                           </note>TO the right Reuerend Fathers, and Lords in Chriſt, the Lords Cardinals, Patriarchs, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates, Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, Embaſſadours, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, &amp; Maſters, and to the whole Councell of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance;</hi> We the Nobles, Lords, Knights, &amp; Eſquires of the famous Marqueſdome of <hi>Morauia,</hi> wiſh the deſire of all Goodneſſe, and the obſeruation of the Commandements of our Lord <hi>IESVS CHRIST,</hi> For aſmuch as euery man, both by the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and by Gods law, is commanded to doe that to another man, which hee would haue done vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, &amp;c. Wee therefore (God being our Author) hauing reſpect, as much as in vs lyeth, vnto the Law of <hi>GOD,</hi> and the loue of our Neighbour, did ſend our Letters vnto <hi>Conſtance,</hi> for our dearely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Friend of good memory, Master <hi>Iohn Huſſe</hi> Bachelor of Diuinity, and Preacher of the Goſpell,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:20231:35"/> whom of late, in the Councell of <hi>Conſtance</hi> (wee know not with what Spirit being led) you haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned as an Hereticke, neither hauing Confeſſed any thing, neither being lawfully Conuict, as was expedient; hauing no errours or Hereſies declared or layd againſt him, but onely at the ſiniſter and falſe accuſations, ſuggeſtions, and inſtigations of his mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Enemies, and the Traytors of our Kingdome and Marqueſdome of <hi>Morauia. And a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> Wherefore wee haue thought good, euen now to direct our Letters Patents to your Reuerences now preſent, in the behalfe of Maſter <hi>Iohn Huſſe,</hi> open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profeſſing and proteſting both with heart and mouth, That hee the ſaid Maſter <hi>Iohn Huſſe,</hi> was a Iuſt, Good, and Catholike man, and for a long ſeaſon worthily commended and allowed in our Kingdome, for his Life and Conuerſation. <hi>And a little after;</hi> So that vſing all the diligence that wee might, wee neuer heard or could vnderſtand, that Maſter <hi>Iohn Huſſe</hi> had Preached, taught, or by any other meanes affirmed any Errour or Hereſie in his Sermons, or that by any manner of meanes hee hath offended Vs or our Subiects, either by word or deed, but that hee hath alwayes led a quiet and Godly life, &amp;c. You haue alſo cruelly Murthered the Worſhipfull man Maſter <hi>Hierome</hi> of <hi>Prague,</hi> a
<pb facs="tcp:20231:36"/> man abounding in Eloquence, Maſter of the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Liberall Artes, and a famous Philoſopher, not being ſeene, heard, or Examined, neither Conuict, but onely at the ſiniſter and falſe accuſation of his and Our accuſer, and betrayers. <hi>And then to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the end of that Epiſtle:</hi> The premiſſes notwithſtanding, Wee ſetting apart all feare of mens ordinances, prouided to the contrary, will Maintayne and Defend the Law of our Lord <hi>IESVS CHRIST,</hi> and the Deuout, humble, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Preachers thereof, euen to the ſhedding of our Blood.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>Dated at</hi> Sternberge, <date>
                                 <hi>in the yeare of our Lord, 1415. vpon St.</hi> Wenceſlaus <hi>day, Martyr of our</hi> Lord <hi>IESVS CHRIST.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>Round about theſe Letters there were 54. Seales hanging, and the Names ſubſcribed, whoſe ſeales they were, who were theſe that follow:
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>ALſſokabat de Wiſcowitz.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Vlricus de L Hota.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ioan: de Kſimicz.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ioſico de Scitowitz.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ioan: de Ziwla.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ioan; de Rheychenberg.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Wildo Skitzini.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Derlico de Biela.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Kos de Doloylatz.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ioan: de Simuſin.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dobeſsimus de Tiſſa.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Drazko de Aradek.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:20231:36"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Steph. de Hmodorka.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ioan: Derne de Babonecx.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Barſo dictus Hloder de Zeinicz.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ioan: Hmurſdorfar.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Plataska de Wilklek.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Petrus de Sczitowcy.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>N. Studenica.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>N. Brilcel.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>N. de Cromaſona.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Aramiſicick Douant.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ioan: Douant.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ioan: Cziczow.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Wenceſſaus de N.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>N. de N.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>N. N.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ioſack de N.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Henricus de N.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Waczlalz de Kuck.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Henric. de Zrenowicz.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Baczkode Conald.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Petrus dictus Nienick de Zaltoroldeck.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Czenko de Moſſnow.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>N. de N.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Zibillutz de Clezan.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ioan: de Paterſwald.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Parſiual: de Namyelkz.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Zodonic de Zwietzik.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ratezek Zawſcalp.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ioan: de Toſſawicz.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Diua de Spiſſna.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Steffko de Drackzdw.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Odich de Hlud.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Wosfar: de Pawlowicz.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pirebbor de Tire zenicz.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Rynard de Tyrczewicz.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bohunko de Wratiſdow.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Vlricus de Wracdraw.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Deſlaw de Nali.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bonesh: de Frohenicz.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Eybl: de Royſſowan.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Whoſe names I thought good heere to annexe, not onely for the more credit of that worthy Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie giuen by theſe Noble men, concerning the Life and Doctrine of <hi>Iohn Huſſe,</hi> and <hi>Hierome</hi> of <hi>Prague;</hi> but alſo to ſhew the great number of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of the <hi>Protestants</hi> Religion in that ſmall part of Chriſtendome, in the Marqueſdome of <hi>Morauia,</hi> and that in a time when <hi>Poperie</hi> did beare ſo great a ſway, whoſe example no doubt many more did follow, ſeeing theſe were Nobles, men of prime note and
<pb facs="tcp:20231:37"/> eſteeme in their Countrey. And thus much may ſuffice for the Apologie of <hi>Iohn Huſſe,</hi> and <hi>Hierome</hi> of <hi>Prague.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Exception a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Iohn Wichleif.</hi>
                  </note> The next of our ancient <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> which the Pope-Catholikes doe except againſt is <hi>Iohn Wichlief;</hi> And what is it that they can except againſt him?<note place="margin">Waldenſ. Epiſt. ad Martin. Ser.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee was</hi> (ſay they) <hi>an hereticke, an hypocrite, a time-ſeruer, a man proud and Ambitious,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ex hiſtor. Mo. naſt. <hi>D.</hi> Albani.</note> 
                  <hi>a ſower of peſtilent and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious Doctrine; And becauſe hee was not preferred to greater honours and dignities of the Church, therefore hee conceiuing indignations againſt the Clergie of theſe times,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Polyd. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgil. in vita Edoard. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came their mortall Enemie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the crime of Hereſie objected againſt him, wee haue already ſhewed,<note place="margin">Apologie for <hi>Iohn Wichleif.</hi>
                  </note> that it is an vſuall thing with the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> to tearme all thoſe Heretickes who withſtand their Popiſh proceedings; let them firſt proue his Doctrine to bee Hereſie, and then they may haue ſome colour for their aſſertion; otherwiſe, their cenſure doth no more preiudice him, then the <hi>Phariſes</hi> did the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 24.14.</note> in counting that Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie which was the true Worſhip of God Almightie. The Councell of <hi>Conſtance</hi> indeed picketh out 45.<note place="margin">Concil. Conſtan. ſs. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> Articles of his Poſitions, which they condemne as Hereticall, diuers whereof, wee confeſſe, may juſtly bee excepted againſt;<note place="margin">Wichleif. in Trid.</note> yet many of them (as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe complaineth) were falſely reported. A thing common with the Enemies of the Truth, to inuent and forge lyes, that ſo they may more freely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame.<note place="margin">Reſponſ. ad <hi>18.</hi> Artic. Wichleif. in Faſcic. rer. Expet.</note> There was one <hi>William Wideford,</hi> who tooke vpon him to anſwere 18. Articles, ſaid to bee <hi>Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chleifs;</hi> whence a man may gather ſome of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; but that all thinges there ſaid againſt him,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:20231:37"/> were not true, may well be obſerued out of the ſame anſwer, declaring that he had many things concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Wichliffe</hi> only by fame and report,<note place="margin">In ſine. Artic. <hi>10</hi>
                  </note> which wee may well know is not alwaies the moſt certaine rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. But ſuppoſe that in his opinions and aſſertions ſome blemiſhes peraduenture may bee noted; yet ſuch blemiſhes they be as rather declare him to bee a man that might erre, then which did directly fight againſt Chriſt our Sauiour, as the Popes procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings and the Friers did. And what Doctor, or learned man hath beene from the prime age of the Church, ſo perfect, and ſo abſolutely ſure, in whom no opinion hath ſometimes ſwerued away?</p>
               <p>As for pride and vaine glory which they taxe in <hi>Wichliffe,</hi> what colour can they haue for that imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; ſeeing that their owne Chronicles doe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme,<note place="margin">Ex hiſtor. Monaſt. D. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bani.</note> that <hi>hee and his fellowes accuſtomed to goe bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>footed, and in ſimple ruſſet Gownes, and in gesture and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour to ſhew much humilitie.</hi> As little ſhew haue they of Ambition, which they taxe in him, or indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation for want of preferment in thoſe times;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>L. Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of</hi> Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terb. p. <hi>66.</hi> Ex Archiu: Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leg. Baliol. Oxon.</note> for neither was his preferment ſo meane, he being both Publike Reader of Diuinitie in the famous Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and alſo head of a Colledge in that Vniuerſitie; And alſo hauing beene employed as an Embaſſadour with certaine other Lords and men of great eſteeme by King <hi>Edward</hi> the third ſent into <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Martyrol. p. <hi>390.</hi>
                  </note> to treate with the Popes Legats concerning the affaires betwixt the King and the Pope,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 393. &amp; 412.</note> with full Commiſſion: The Copie whereof <hi>Extat. Acts &amp; Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. p.</hi> 390. Moreouer, what dignitie or preferment
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:20231:38"/> here in <hi>England</hi> could haue beene wanting vnto him, had he ambitiouſly affected the ſame,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jbid. p.</hi> 393. &amp; 412.</note> hauing ſuch e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciall Patrons as the King himſelfe, the Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> Earle <hi>Percie</hi> Lord Marſhall, the Earle of <hi>Salisburie,</hi> and diuers others of the greateſt in Land, who continually tooke his part, and ſtood with him?</p>
               <p>Moreouer as concerning his great Learning, wee haue the confeſſion of Frier <hi>Walden,</hi> his moſt cruell and bitter enemie, who in a certaine Epiſtle written to Pope <hi>Martin</hi> the fift ſaith,<note place="margin">Walden. Epiſt. ad Martin. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>That he was wonderfully aſtoniſhed at his moſt ſtrong Arguments, with the places of authoritie which he had gathered, with the vehemencie and force of his reaſons, &amp;c.</hi> And for further Teſtimonie both of his life and learning, heare the publike Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall of the whole Vniuerſitie of <hi>Oxford</hi> giuen vnto him and his memorie; The Copie whereof fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>VNto all and ſingular the Children of our holy Mother the Church, to whom this preſent Letter ſhall come, the Vice-Chancelor of the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of <hi>Oxford,</hi> with the whole congregation of the Maſters wiſh perpetuall health in the LORD. For as much as it is not commenly ſeene, that the Acts and Monuments of valiant men, nor the praiſe and merrits of good men ſhould be paſſed ouer, &amp;c. Hereupon it followeth, that the ſpeciall good will and care which we beare vnto <hi>Iohn Wichliffe,</hi> ſometime
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:20231:38"/> childe of our Vniuerſitie, and Profeſſor of Diuinitie, mouing and ſtirring our mindes (as his manners and conditions required no leſſe) with one minde, voice, and teſtimonie, we doe all witneſſe, all his conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and doings throughout his whole life, to haue beene moſt ſincere and commendable; whoſe honeſt manners and conditions, profoundneſſe of Learning, and most redolent Renowne and fame, we deſire the more earneſtly to be notified and knowne to all the faithfull; For that we vnderſtand the maturitie and ripeneſſe of his conuerſation, his diligent labours and trauailes to tend to the praiſe of God, the helpe and ſafegard of others, and the profit of the Church. Wherefore we ſignifie vnto you by theſe preſents, that his conuerſation euen from his youth vpwards, vnto the time of his death, was ſo praiſe-worthy and honeſt, that neuer at any time was there any note or ſpot of ſuſpition noyſed of him, But in his anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, reading; preaching, and determining, He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haued himſelfe laudibly, and as a ſtout and valiant Champion of the Faith, vanquiſhing by the force of the Scriptures, all ſuch who by their wilfull begge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie blaſpheamed and ſlaundered Chriſts Religion. Neither was this ſaid Doctor conuict of any here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, or burned by our Prelates: God forbid that our
<pb facs="tcp:20231:39"/> Prelates ſhould haue condemned a man of ſuch honeſtie, for an Hereticke, who among all the reſt of the Vniuerſitie, hath written in Logicke, Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie, Diuinitie, Moralitie, and the Speculatiue Art, without peere. The knowledge of which, all and ſingular things, wee doe deſire to teſtifie and deliuer forth, to the intent that the fame and renowne of this ſaid Doctor, may bee the more euident, and had in reputation among them, vnto whoſe hands theſe preſent Letters teſtimoniall ſhall come.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>In witneſſe whereof, wee haue cauſed theſe our Letters teſtimoniall to be Sealed with our common Seale. Dated at</hi> Oxford, <hi>in the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion houſe</hi> 
                           <date>the <hi>5. day of October, in the yeare of our Lord. 1406.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Thus farre of Doctor <hi>Wickliffe,</hi> and of the cauils which the Papiſts doe obiect againſt him; The next that eſpecially they except againſt in the Catalogue before recited, are the <hi>Waldenſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exceptions againſt the</hi> Waldenſes. Laziardus. Volaterranus. Syluius.</note>And what haue they to except againſt theſe <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe Waldenſes</hi> (ſay they) <hi>were a beggerly raskall ſort of people, ignorant and vnlearned, ſeditious, factious, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of euill opinions, and among the reſt, they would
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:20231:39"/> haue all things common among them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To that exception of Papiſts againſt the pouertie of theſe <hi>Waldenſes</hi> wee anſwer. 1.<note place="margin">Apologie for the <hi>Waldenſes.</hi>
                  </note> That pouertie can be no diſgrace vnto them who liue vprightly, and maintaine the truth in ſinceritie,<note place="margin">Prou. 19.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Better is the poore that walketh in his integritie, then the rich that is peruerſe; hath not God choſen the poore of this world, rich in faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 2.5.</note> 
                  <hi>and heires of the kingdome of heauen?</hi> 2. Neither yet were they all in ſuch pouertie,<note place="margin">Hiſtor. Walden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſium.</note> for <hi>Waldus</hi> (whom they call the ring leader of them) was a man of great ſubſtance, <hi>Reymund</hi> Earle of <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> and diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great Potentates adhered to them and their Religion. 3. Neither was their number ſo ſmall, or themſelues ſuch vagabonds as the Papiſts doe tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> for though the fury of perſecution did diſperſe diuers of them, and cauſed them to flie from place to place, yet they followed their callings, and many times valiantly defeated their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
               <p>To the want of learning, and groſſe ignorance, which the Papiſts obiect againſt them, I anſwer, firſt with that of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.26.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.26, 27, 28.</note> 
                  <hi>Not many wiſe men after the fleſh, not many mightie, not many No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hath God called but God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world to confound the wiſe, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.1.</note> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>That they are beſt learned, who haue learned to know Ieſus Chriſt and him crucified.</hi> Secondly, wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie that they were all ſo illiterate or vnlearned. <hi>Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerus</hi> a Writer about that time, and a bitter enemie of theirs, in a long proceſſe, wherein hee deſcribeth
<pb facs="tcp:20231:40"/> their Doctrine, teſtifieth that hee heard of one who did know the partie,<note place="margin">Reyner. de Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſ.</note> 
                  <hi>that a certaine hereticke of this ſect</hi> (ſo it pleaſeth him to ſtile them) <hi>to conuert a certaine perſon to his faith, in the night and Winter time, ſwamme ouer the Riuer</hi> Ibis <hi>to come vnto him, and to teach him: Moreouer ſo perfect</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>were they in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that hee himſelfe did ſee and heare a man of the Countrey vnlettered; which could recite ouer the whole booke of</hi> Iob <hi>word by word without booke, with diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which had the whole new Teſtament perfectly by heart.</hi> And although ſome of them rather merrily then vnskilfully expounded the words, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.12. <hi>Sui non receperunt cum;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aenaeus Sylu. Bohem. hiſt. de Waldenſ. dogmat.</note> 
                  <hi>Swine did not receiue him;</hi> yet were they nor ſo ignorant and voide of learning, but that in <hi>Reynerus</hi> his time they <hi>had</hi> 40. <hi>Churches at the leaſt, and Paſtors to instruct them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reyner. reſp.</note> 
                  <hi>and in one Pariſh called</hi> Cammach, <hi>there were tenne open Schooles of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And whereas they are taxed by <hi>Aeneus Siluius</hi> to ſauour of an Anabaſtinill communitie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Martyrol.</hi> 209.</note> 
                  <hi>that they had all things common among them,</hi> This is a malicious ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of a papall Paraſite; Indeed becauſe they being thruſt forth both of Countrie and goods, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to make the beſt ſhift as they could for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, they did not intend their owne priuate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie, but euery one did helpe each other to the vtmoſt of his power, the moſt part of them being made through the Tyrannie of their perſecutors ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry poore; and hence they were called <hi>Pauperes de Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>o, Or the poore men of Lyons.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:20231:40"/>
               <p>Their Doctrine, howſoeuer the Papiſts (after their vſuall manner) miſ-report of it, and ſpeake worſe of it then it is, yet cannot be brought by them within the compaſſe of Hereſie, or be confuted by the Word of God. The Booke of Inquiſition doth thus deſcribe them and their manners:<note place="margin">Ex Inquiſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio quodam li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bello de mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etudine Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſ.</note> 
                  <hi>The manner of the Waldenſis is this; They kneeling vpon their knees, doe continue in their prayers with ſilence, ſo long as a man may ſay thirtie or fortie Pater-noſters: And this they doe euery day with great reuerence, being among themſelues, and ſuch as be of their owne Religion, both before Meales, and after; likewiſe when they goe to bed, and in the morning when they riſe, and at certaine other times alſo, as well in the Day as in the Night. Alſo they haue and vſe the ſeuen Articles of Faith concerning the Diuinitie, and ſeuen Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles concerning the Humanitie, and the ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſeuen workes of Mercie, which they haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyled together in a compendious Booke, glorying much in the ſame, and thereby offer themſelues readie to anſwere any man for their Faith. Before they goe to meat, they haue this Grace;</hi> Benedicite, Kyrie eleyſon, Chriſte eleyſon, Kyrie eleyſon, Pater-noſter: <hi>Which being ſaid, then the elder amongſt them beginneth thus in their owne Tongue;</hi> God which bleſſed the fiue Barley Loaues and two Fiſhes in the Deſart, before his Diſciples, bleſſe this Table, and that which is or ſhall be ſet vpon it, In the Name of the Father, of the Sonne, and the Holy Ghoſt, Amen. <hi>And likewiſe when they riſe from meat, the Senior giueth thankes, ſaying the words of the</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calypſe; Bleſſing, and Worſhip, and Wiſdome, and Thankſ-giuing, Honor, Vertue, and Strength to God alone for euermore, Amen. <hi>And addeth moreouer;</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:20231:41"/> God reward them in their Boſomes, and be beneficiall to all them that be beneficiall to vs, and bleſſe vs: And the God which hath giuen vs Corporall Feeding, graunt vs Spirituall Life; and God be with vs, and wee alwayes with him: <hi>To which they all anſwere,</hi> Amen. <hi>And thus ſaying Grace, they hold their hands vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, looking vp to Heauen. After their Meat, and Grace thus ſaid they teach and exhort among themſelues, confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring together vpon their Doctrine, &amp;c.</hi> Hitherto the Booke of Inquiſition made againſt them, doth teſtifie of them.</p>
               <p>Let vs adde hereto the Teſtimonie of <hi>Reynerus,</hi> their profeſſed Enemie; who when hee had ſaid all that he could, in deprauing and impugning them, yet is driuen to confeſſe this of them:<note place="margin">Reyner. Hiſt. de Waldenſ. Ex Orthuin. Gratian.</note> 
                  <hi>This Sect of Lyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſts</hi> (ſo hee calleth them, of the place where-hence firſt they ſprang) <hi>hath great ſhew of Pietie, liuing vprightly before men, and beleeuing all things aright concerning God, and all the Articles of the Creed, onely they hate and blaſpheme the Church of Rome, &amp;c.</hi> Thus farre, by way of Apologie, for the Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſes.</p>
               <p>The like Apologie I might make for all the reſt of thoſe famous Worthies, which together with vs, long before our dayes, or the dayes of <hi>Martin Luther</hi> haue profeſſed the ſame Religion which wee now profeſſe. But becauſe theſe, before-mentioned, are the parties againſt whom our Aduerſaries (the Papiſts) eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally doe except; and whatſoeuer elſe they doe, or can alleadge againſt any other particulars, are the ſame things which haue beene anſwered vnto the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer exceptions; I will ſurceaſe from further Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:20231:41"/> eſpecially ſeeing that I labour to be briefe. This (which this way hath beene ſpoken) may ſuffice, to cleare theſe Auncients of our Religion (whom wee haue alreadie prooued to haue beene of the ſame Faith and Religion which wee now hold, and the Papiſts themſelues call the fore-runners of our Faith) from thoſe ſlanderous Calumniations which they aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe vpon them, and to prooue them ſuch famous and worthie Inſtruments of Gods glorie, that wee need not be aſhamed to follow them in that holy way which they haue gone before vs.</p>
               <p>Hauing now cleared the way, and traced the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of our Proteſtant predeceſſors backward, from the dayes of <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> vnto the very time when Poperie (that great Myſterie of Iniquitie) began to diſplay it ſelfe in her colours, from the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, vnto the dayes of <hi>Phocas</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, for the ſpace well-nigh of a thouſand yeeres; I now returne againe to proſecute this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue, and to ſhew a farre higher aſcent of the ſame, from the time when Poperie was ſet on foot, vnto the dayes of the Apoſtles, and the time in which our bleſſed Sauiour did manifeſt himſelfe in the fleſh.</p>
               <p>Which labour, albeit it might well be ſpared, for as much as the Controuerſie being betweene vs and the Papiſts, Which of the two Churches is the moſt auncienteſt; wee hauing alreadie ſhewed the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of our Church, euen from the time when firſt their Church (if wee may call that a Church, which they haue turned into a Court) began, wee haue done alreadie to ſtop their mouthes, and to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:20231:42"/> free our ſelues from that imputation of Noueltie which they obiect againſt vs: Yet for the more am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple manifeſting of the Point now in Controuerſie, and wholly to ſtop the mouth of the Aduerſarie, that it may appeare that our Religion is yet of farre grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Antiquitie; a farther demonſtration ſhall be made, wherein it ſhall appeare, that our Religion (that which is now profeſſed by the Proteſtant Churches) is that ſame Religion which was taught by Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, profeſſed and maintained by all the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxe ancient Fathers, Martyrs, and Confeſſors, that liued in and ſince the Primitiue Church, to the time that Poperie was firſt hatched out of his Cockatrice Egge.</p>
               <p>Which to make plaine, wee muſt by the way take notice, That in the firſt ſix hundred yeeres there was no ſubſtantiall or fundamentall Innouation receiued in the Church; the preſent Romane Faith (touching the Points controuerted betweene them and vs) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as yet eyther vnhatched, or not receiued by knowne Heretikes:<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.7.</note> Onely the Myſterie of Iniquitie that began to worke in the Apoſtles time,<note place="margin">Euſeb. Hiſt. lib. 3. cap. 32. lib. 4. cap. 23.</note> encreaſed by the Hereſie, Ignorance, and Superſtition of ſome that dayly corrupted the Truth. Stories remember vs of a ſaying of <hi>Hegeſippus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Niceph. lib. 4. cap. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>That the Church conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued a Virgin vndefiled, as long as the Apoſtles liued: but when that generation was paſt, the conſpiracie of wicked Hereſie, through the ſeducing of thoſe who taught other Doctrine, tooke beginning.</hi> Hereof the Apoſtles gaue warning,<note place="margin">Act. 20.28. Philip. 3.18. Baſil. Ep. 70.</note> and the auncient Fathers complayned, and that with teares. It is our Taske now to prooue, that all thoſe faithfull Chriſtians,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:20231:42"/> who liued either in the primitiue pureſt times, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards kept themſelues orthodoxe, vnſpotted from then-broached hereſies, till the hereſie of hereſies, Poperie was ſet on foote, were of the ſame faith and religion with vs, and were of our ſide: for the triall whereof, as we haue already looked into the dayes of olde,<note place="margin">Deut. 32.7.</note> and conſidered the yeares of many generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are paſt and gone; ſo now let vs aske our Fathers, and they will ſhew vs, let vs aske our Elders, and they will tell vs.</p>
               <p>And here as the Papiſts challenge vs to ſhew where our Church was before <hi>Luthers</hi> time, wee will ſhew our Church before the time of Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the 3. who was the firſt that tooke vpon him the name of the vniuerſall Biſhop, and at whom (and not before) the Popiſh Church (as now it is) doth take her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. This <hi>Boniface</hi> about the yeare of our Lord 507. with much adoe obtained of <hi>Phocas</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,<note place="margin">Otho Friſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen. Chron. lib. 5. c. 8. Marian Scot. in ann. 608. Vſperg. in Phoca.</note> that he might be made the vniuerſall Biſhop of the world: The which authority (ſay the Romane Chroniclers) his ſucceſſours haue not onely held faſt with their teeth, but alſo wonderfully encreaſed. Before this time, or before there was euer any who vſurped any ſuch Eccleſiaſticall Supremacie, wee haue many that tooke our part, as may appeare by this Induction.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:20231:43"/>
               <head>Betweene the yeares 450. <hi>and</hi> 500.</head>
               <p>In Rome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>GRegory</hi> the 1. who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit hee did much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline from the ſincerity of his pious predeceſſours, and was a pat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on or many ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, yet was an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt oppoſite againſt the pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pall Supremacie, calling it vaine, proud, profane, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous, miſchieuous, An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tichriſtian, againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of God, and the decrees of Councels. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 32.34. affirming him to be a follower of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, &amp; fore-runner of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, who aſſumeth that title. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 38.39.</p>
               <p n="24">24. Biſhops, and 34. Preſbiters in a Councell at Rome. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 595.</p>
               <p>Jn Conſtantinople.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euphemius,</hi> who was ſo firme and conſtant in his Religion, that he would not annoint <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, before he had ſealed a writing that he would make no innouation in Religion. <hi>Theod. lib.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>Jn Alexandria.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> called <hi>Tabeneſiota,</hi> who kept the true ſaith, and was baniſhed by <hi>Anaſtaſius,</hi> becauſe hee would not damne the counſell of <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon. Magdeb. cent.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>In Antiochiae.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregorius</hi> who miniſtred in <hi>Antiochia</hi> 25. yeares, how he adhaered to our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: ſee <hi>Euagr. li.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 18.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Betweene the yeares 400. and 450.</head>
               <p>Jn Rome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>LEo,</hi> at the firſt a Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, afterwards Biſhop of Rome, among whoſe conſtitutions there is a ſharpe decree againſt the ambition, which euen then beganne in that ſea. <hi>Hiſt. Magd. cent.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>Jn Conſtantinople.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Chryſoſtome,</hi> Biſhop of Conſtantinople, who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the dayes of <hi>Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> &amp; <hi>Honorius:</hi> In whoſe
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:20231:43"/> writings we may find moſt part of thoſe points, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee differ from the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts confirmed: As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Atticus</hi> another Biſhop of Conſtantinople, who next ſaue one ſucceeded <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in that ſea, was a bitter enemie to ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for perceauing that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of the people of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople, ſorted to the Sepulchre of <hi>Sabbatius,</hi> to pray &amp; to do ſome worſhip to your defunct; he cauſed that body in the night ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be raiſed, and to be buried in another place vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to the ſaid ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious people, that ſo they might leaue off their Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous praying. <hi>Hiſt. Magd. cent.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Accatius</hi> another Biſhop of Conſtantinople ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Gennadius,</hi> and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that ſea 17. yeares. In his time the Roman Church contended for ſuperiority. This <hi>Acatius</hi> reſiſted the fame, and little regarding the pride of the Romane, Biſhop, excommunicated <hi>Foelix,</hi> and razed his name out of the roll of Biſhops. <hi>Hiſtor, Magd. Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Jn Syria.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theodoret</hi> Biſhop of Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus a Towne in Syria, liued vnder the Emperours <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius, Valentinian, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian:</hi> Among other things wherein hee agreeth with vs, hee is directly againſt tranſubſtantiation. <hi>Theod. dial.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>Jn Affrica.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Biſhop of Hippo, one of the moſt learned of all the auncient Fathers, his Religion was the ſame with vs, as may appeare in theſe enſuing ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s about.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The ſufficiencie of Scripture. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de pec. meri. c.</hi> 36. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de doct. Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The Laities reading the Scripture. <hi>confeſ. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp; in Pſal.</hi> 33. <hi>ſeſs.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The markes of the Church. <hi>de vnitat. eccl. c.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p n="4">4. O iginall ſinne. <hi>enchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid. ad laur. c.</hi> 92.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Good works. <hi>in Pſal.</hi> 102.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Sacraments. <hi>tract.</hi> 15. <hi>in Ioh. &amp; de ſymbol, ad catech. &amp; tract.</hi> 30. <hi>in Ioh. &amp; contra Adamant. c.</hi> 12. <hi>&amp; tract.</hi> 30. <hi>in Joh. &amp; de ciuit.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:20231:44"/> dei. lib.</hi> 21. <hi>c.</hi> 25.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The authority of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Councels. <hi>Ser.</hi> 2. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 162.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Inuocation of Saints. <hi>tract.</hi> 19. <hi>in Iohn. &amp; contr. Fauſt. Manich. lib.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>See farther S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> agreement with vs in the maine points of faith and doctrine, in a Treatiſe late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet forth to this purpoſe, entituled <hi>S. Auguſtines Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> wherein are proued 62. points of our and his concordance.</p>
               <p>Jn France.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eleutherius</hi> Biſh. of Lions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saluianus</hi> Biſh. of Marſell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hilarius,</hi> firſt Biſhop of Arles, afterwards of Vien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, oppoſed himſelfe direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt <hi>Leo</hi> Biſhop of Rome, and would acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge no iuriſdiction of that Sea, ouer the Churches of France: he came to Rome, and withſtood the Pope to his face. <hi>Leo ad Gal. Epiſc. epiſt.</hi> 77. <hi>&amp;</hi> 89.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Vincentius Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinenſis. Magd. cent.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Proſper Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanicus. Magd. cent.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Martinus Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronenſis. Magd. cent.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Betweene the yeeres 350. and 400.</head>
               <p>In Jtaly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AMbroſe,</hi> Biſhop of Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane, whoſe accord with vs in the maine points of our Religion may appeare out of his writings. <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hierome</hi> borne in Stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, a Towne of Dalmatia, brought vp in learning at Rome, who although hee wanted not his errours, and enclined much to diuers ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, which began a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thoſe times, yet accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in many things with vs, as may appeare by his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings.</p>
               <p>Jn Antiochia.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Flauianus,</hi> againſt whom <hi>Damaſus, Syricius,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtaſius,</hi> Biſhops of Rome, were mighty oppoſites, who miſinformed the good Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Theodoſius</hi> againſt him, before whom when <hi>Flauianus</hi> had appeared, he freely and wiſely ſpake to this effect. <hi>O Emperour, if any man blame my faith as peruerſe, or my life as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, I am content to bee
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:20231:44"/> iudged by my very Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: But if the Diſputation be onely concerning Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and eminent places, I will not contend with any man, but denude my ſelfe of all Superioritie, and commit the charge of Antiochia to whom yee like beſt.</hi> Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor. lib. 5. c. 23.</p>
               <p>In Jeruſalem.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cyrillus,</hi> who was an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to the Pompe of the Clergie, and had more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to feede the Poore, and to the Preaching of the Word, then to the outward garniſhing of Churches. <hi>Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zomen. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 25.</p>
               <p>Jn Conſtantinople.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nectarius,</hi> a man of noble birth, Biſhop of Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople; in whoſe time, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricular Confeſſion was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brogated in Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, vpon occaſion of Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie committed betweene a Penitentiarie and a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, confeſſing her ſinnes vnto him. <hi>Socrat. lib</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 19.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Councell of Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon.</head>
               <p>Where, was the Emperor <hi>Martianus</hi> himſelfe in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and of Biſhops and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Fathers, 630. Theſe in plaine tearmes, gaue the Sea of Conſtantinople equall Priuiledges with Rome, and in cauſes Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall, to be aduanced as farre as Rome. <hi>Concilium Chalced. Act.</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>In Armenia.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Letoius,</hi> Biſhop of Mele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina, in Armenia, a bitter e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie to Monkiſh Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whoſe ſocietie hee was wont to call a Denne of Theeues. <hi>Theodot. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>Jn Affrica.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Optatus Mileuitanus,</hi> who liued about this time, and doth accord with vs; firſt, in the Scriptures, that they are the Iudge of Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies, <hi>Lib.</hi> 6, <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Script.</hi> ſecondly, about the Sacraments, <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 1. <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bus ibi eſt spiritualis, &amp; potus spiritualis:</hi> In the Point of Regeneration, <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7. In the Point of the Catholike Church, <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>aduerſus Parmen.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:20231:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Jn Europe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hilarius,</hi> Biſhop of Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers in France, who tooke great paines to purge the Countrey of Fraunce from the Arrian Hereſie, and to withdraw the people from Superſtition. <hi>Ruffin. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 31. <hi>Hiſtor. Magdeb. Cent.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Betweene the yeeres 300. and 350.</head>
               <p>Councels.</p>
               <p>THe Councels of Ancy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, Nice, Tyrus, Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gra (in which was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Hereſie of <hi>Euſtaſius</hi> ſpeaking againſt Marriage, eating of Fleſh, &amp;c.) Elibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, Carthage (where the Biſhop of Rome was ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly withſtood) Antioch, and Sardica, were all ſummoned at the commaundement of the Emperours, not of the Popes. <hi>Tom. Concil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fathers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Baſilius Magnus,</hi> Biſhop of Caeſarea in Cappadocia, in his Writings hee much confirmeth our Faith, and Doctrine, and complaineth of the pride of the Weſterne Churches, and condemneth their affectation of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie. <hi>Baſil. tranſmarin. Epiſt.</hi> 77. <hi>&amp; Epiſt.</hi> 10. <hi>ad Euſamoſ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregorius Nazianzenus,</hi> who reuiued the true life of Preaching, when the Truth of GOD ſeemed to haue beene buried, and inueigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the pride of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, ſeeking Supremacie ouer others. <hi>Zozom. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregorius Nyſſenus,</hi> a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Biſhop. <hi>Niceph. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. whoſe Writings albeit the Papiſts doe alleage in many places, to patronize their doctrines and opinions; yet beeing well conſidered, they make nothing for them, but rather much againſt them. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ide Sculleti examen locorum ex Nyſſeno a Pontif. citat. in medulla Patr.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Macarius Aegyptius,</hi> a learned Writer, is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with vs in the point of Iuſtification, <hi>Hom.</hi> 11: in the certaintie of Saluation, <hi>Homil.</hi> 19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20. againſt
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:20231:45"/> the Reall preſence, <hi>Hom.</hi> 27. againſt Purgatory, <hi>Hom.</hi> 30, 44. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22. againſt Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, <hi>Hom.</hi> 2, 27.15, 46.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſebius Caeſarienſis,</hi> a learned man, and writer of many Bookes, agreeth with vs againſt the Papall Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie, <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de vit. Const. &amp;</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 37. about the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Hiſtor. Eccl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ. c.</hi> 14. about the Sacraments, <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>demonſt. c.</hi> 10. <hi>&amp; li.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. about Iuſtification, <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Hiſtor. Eccleſ. cap.</hi> 5. againſt Images, <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de praep. Euang.</hi> againſt Popiſh Iniunctions of Faſtings, <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Eccleſ. Hiſt. c.</hi> 23.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> borne in a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Village of Paleſtina, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Barſanduce; hee wrote much, and in his Writings agreeth with vs, concerning the Scriptures, <hi>Lib. de menſ.</hi> and power of the Catholike Church, <hi>Haereſ.</hi> 35. about Marriage, and Virginitie, <hi>Haereſ.</hi> 48. about Faſting, <hi>Haereſ.</hi> 33. againſt inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Saints, <hi>Haereſ.</hi> 78, 79. againſt Images, <hi>Haereſ.</hi> 19. againſt the Maſſe, <hi>Haereſ.</hi> 55. againſt Purgatorie, <hi>Haereſ.</hi> 59. againſt celebrating of Prieſts, <hi>Haereſ.</hi> 61. againſt Lay-Baptiſme, <hi>Haereſ.</hi> 76.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> Biſhop of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria, whoſe name was famous in the elder Church, wrote much, and agreeth therein with vs: Againſt Traditions, <hi>Epiſt. de Synod. Niceu. Decr.</hi> againſt Inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Saints, <hi>Epiſt. ad Adelph.</hi> againſt their ſeuen Sacraments, <hi>Orat.</hi> 2. <hi>contra Arrian.</hi> againſt Images, <hi>Orat. contra Gentes:</hi> againſt the Supremacie, <hi>Epiſtol. ad Solit.</hi> and many other ſuch like points.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paphnutius,</hi> a Biſhop in a Towne of Thebaida, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe an vnmarried man, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed himſelfe in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Nice, againſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition of Prieſts marriage, and cauſed the ſame to bee ſtayed, <hi>Socrat. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lactantius Firmianus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Didymus,</hi> a Doctor of the Schoole of Alexandria.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acholius,</hi> Biſhop of Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonica.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oſius,</hi> Biſhop of Corduba.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aſclepas,</hi> in Gaza.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philogonius,</hi> Biſhop of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochia.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hermogenes,</hi> Biſhop of Caeſarea.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>James,</hi> Biſhop of Niſebis, in Meſopotamia, and diuers others.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:20231:46"/>
               <p>Thus haue I ſhewed the fore-runners of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, aboue two hundred yeeres before Poperie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan; and the Profeſſors of the ſame, in the time of the Churches flouriſhing eſtate, before the Church of Rome declined to that Apoſtaſie, in which now for theſe many yeeres, it hath continued. Whereby wee may diſcerne, how impudent our Aduerſaries the Papiſts are,<note place="margin">Campian. rat. 5.</note> in challenging all the ancient Fathers as theirs; and making no end of boaſting of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,<note place="margin">Greg. Valenc tom. 3. p. 291.</note> one of them ſaith: <hi>The Proteſtants, in the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of Faith, ſhould enquire on what ſide the Fathers ſtand, that it being knowne, they might embrace the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which the Fathers of old iudged to be true.</hi> Wee haue done as hee aduiſeth: Wee haue asked the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and they haue told vs; our Elders, and they haue told vs, That they haue profeſſed and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the ſame Doctrine and Religion which wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe. True it is indeede, wee dare not follow euery one of them in euerie ſtep, or tye our ſelues to euery one of their Opinions. The Fathers themſelues were men; and beeing men, might haue, yea had their Errors. Onely the Canonicall Authors (as the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit himſelfe confeſſeth) as being from aboue, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly and Diuine,<note place="margin">Greg. Valenc. tom. 3. p. 329.</note> doe alwayes hold a perpetuall and ſtable conſtancie in their Writings: But other holy Writers are inferior, and humane, failing ſometimes, and now and then, contrarie to the courſe of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,<note place="margin">Epiph. de not.</note> bring foorth a Monſter. <hi>Origen</hi> taught many things againſt the Faith, and miſ-applyed many things in Scripture:<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Iub. aduerſ. Prax. Auguſt. d. 9. Negare.</note> 
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> held Rebaptization; <hi>Tertullian,</hi> Montaniſme: And which of them had not his faylings? <hi>Auguſtine</hi> himſelfe ſaith; <hi>I cannot
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:20231:46"/> denie, but that there are many things in my workes, as there are alſo in the writings of mine Anceſtors, which iuſtly and with good diſcretion may be blamed.</hi> The Fathers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues haue denied what ſome of their Fathers haue held before them; yea, ſome of them vpon better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration haue retracted their owne errors; we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (according to <hi>Marſilius</hi> his aduice) <hi>receiue what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they bring conſonant to the Scripture,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Marſil. Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor. pacis, p. 413.</note> 
                  <hi>but what they bring diſſonant from it, we reiect with reuerence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a falſe ſlaunder therefore which the Ieſuites and other ſuch like Popiſh circumcellions buzze into the eares of their peruerted Proſelites;<note place="margin">Briſto. Motiu. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>That we Proteſtants diſclaime the Fathers, deſpiſe their writings, ſhunne the triall of our doctrine by them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Campian. rat. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe</hi> (ſay they) <hi>we know that they are all againſt vs.</hi> Whether wee or they doe leaſt eſteeme the writings of the Fathers; let the indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Reader iudge. They boaſt and bragge of, but how baſely doe they vilifie them, and proudly reiect them, where they doe not fit their humours?<note place="margin">Bellar. Rom. Pontif. lib. 4. c. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Little cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bellarmine) is to be giuen to</hi> Tertullian <hi>in this matter, for he was a Montaniſt; I doe not in this point</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tolet) allow the doctrine of</hi> Auguſtine, Ambroſe,<note place="margin">Tolet. Rom. 9. p. 421.</note> Chryſoſtome, Theodoret, <hi>and</hi> Photius. <hi>I will ſooner beleeue</hi> Anacletus (ſaith <hi>Alphonſus) then either</hi> Hierome <hi>or</hi> Auguſtine: <hi>Though</hi> Chryſoſtome <hi>and</hi> Auguſtine,<note place="margin">Alphonſ. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. haer. verb. Epiſcop.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſome other Fathers ſay (That</hi> Iudas <hi>receiued the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) yet the conſtitution of</hi> Clement <hi>(an egregious coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit)</hi> ſaith another of them, <hi>is rather to be beleeued.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Turrian. Scho. Graec. in Conſt. p. 172.</note> In the matter touching the Baptiſme of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, they reiect <hi>Euſebius, Ambroſe, Hierome, Theodoret,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Baron. an. 324. n. 43. &amp; 50.</note> 
                  <hi>Socrates, Zozomen,</hi> and the whole Councell of Arimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, and ſay, That they deſerue no credit. In the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:20231:47"/> about the Conception of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Almain. poteſt. Eccleſ. c. 16.</note> they hold her to be exempted from Originall ſinne, and make it a point of Faith ſo to beleeue,<note place="margin">Bann. part. 1. p. 75.</note> and that it is impietie to thinke otherwiſe; yet they acknowledge, that all the Fathers with one conſent held the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary. Thus do they dodge with the Fathers, &amp; caſt them off contumeliouſly, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they do not dance after their Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Pipe; and yet would ſeeme wholly to relye vpon them, and to ſeeke the tryall of their Cauſe by them.</p>
               <p>No wonder then if they find Cauils at our Quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, caſting off moſt violently whatſoeuer is alledged by vs out of the Writings of thoſe Fathers, onely becauſe they will not be ſaid to haue yeelded, that Councels, Fathers, Hiſtories, or any auncient Writers ſhould ſeeme to be of our ſide. Whatſoeuer wee produce, they ſleightly put off with one anſwere, <hi>It is forged.</hi> Inſtance wee in the Hiſtorie of <hi>Honorius,</hi> the Pope, and ſhew his falling into the error of the Monothelites;<note place="margin">Nicen. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. 2. Bellarm. de Rom. Pontif. lib. 4. c. 11. Concil. 6. ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerali. Pyggh. diatrib. de Act. 6. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod. Baron. an. 681. n. 13. Bellarm. vt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra. Baron. an. 181. n. 31. Quem voluiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſem ſenſibus potius Canum quam nomine.</note> they will tell vs, We doe belye him: Alledge we for proofe, the ſecond Nicene Councell; they anſwere, The Councell is forged: Second wee yet with the teſtimonie of the ſixt General Councell; they will reply, That part of the Councell which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth his Condemnation, is forged by the Greekes: Alledge we the eight Generall Councell, to backe it; they will reply, That Councell was deceiued by the falſe Copies of the ſixt Synod: Alledge we diuers au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentike Hiſtories, that ſay it; they will anſwere in a word, by denying their authoritie: Alledge we further ſome of their owne Writers (as <hi>Canus</hi>) that acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged it; they reiect him, and deſcant vpon his name, wiſhing, That he had more wit, then to be ſo headlong
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:20231:47"/> in giuing his verdict vpon ſo great a matter. So when we doe obiect the ſixt Councell of Carthage,<note place="margin">Concil. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thag. 6. c. 3.</note> ſtoutly reſiſting the Pope of Rome, and conuincing him of Forgerie; they will anſwere,<note place="margin">Apolog. pro Ieſ. p. 99.</note> That was no true Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell. Make wee it plaine, that it was a true Councell, and that there were 217. Biſhops at that Councell,<note place="margin">Socrat. lib. 6. c. 18.</note> who openly withſtood the Biſhop of Rome, and taxed him for forging ſome falſely pretended Canons of the Nicene Councell; they will reply,<note place="margin">Apol. pro. Ieſ. p. 103.</note> Thoſe Biſhops of Africa were deceiued in the number of the Nicene Canons: Prooue we this not to be ſo, by producing forth the Acts of the Councell; they ſhift it off,<note place="margin">Bonifac. 2. ad Eulal. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concil. Concil. Carthag. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Concil. tom. 1. Concil. Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon. Act. 16.</note> with exclayming againſt the Fathers aſſembled in the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage Councell, and ſay, That the Deuill led them to be ſo ſawcie with the Biſhop of Rome. So produce we the Councell of Chalcedon, giuing equall priuiledges to the Biſhop of Conſtantinople with the Biſhop of Rome; they reply,<note place="margin">Apol. pro Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit.</note> The Vice-gerents of the See Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolike, <hi>Paſchaſinus</hi> &amp; <hi>Lucentius,</hi> were not preſent when that Decree was made, therefore that Decree was not good. Wee confirme, that afterward,<note place="margin">B. Bilſons diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene Chriſtian ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, p. 79.</note> when they were preſent, &amp; deſired to haue that Act reuoked, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell did confirme it; they reply, The more to blame they were that did it: and exclaime againſt that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell for ratifying it, when the Biſhop of Rome reſiſted it. By theſe few examples we may ſee what ſmall rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning the Papiſts make of Antiquitie, if it run againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neuer ſo litle; &amp; that notwithſtanding their big pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of the ancient Fathers, they are fain to reiect the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at euery turne. Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anſwer to B. <hi>Iuels</hi> Challe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, to B. <hi>Bilſons</hi> Treatiſe, &amp; to the reſt of our writers, who haue offred the trial of our cauſe, &amp; the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſie between
<pb facs="tcp:20231:48" rendition="simple:additions"/> vs and them, to be decided by the Fathers; and they ſhall plainely ſee, we want not teſtimonie of Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: and that the ancient Fathers of the Church (as our learned <hi>Whitakers</hi> well obſerueth) <hi>where they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, are with vs, and onely theirs, in their errors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I proceed now forward in my Catalogue to the firſt two hundred yeares, which was the time of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches perſecution, at what time as it groaned vnder the tyrannie of the perſecuting Romane Emperours: At what time by reaſon of the great and grieuous perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which were raiſed againſt the faithfull Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, they could not haue ſuch free meetings, and publique congregations, but were driuen from place to place, vexed, afflicted, and tormented; yet euen then there were not wanting thouſands who did profeſſe the ſame Faith and Doctrine which wee now follow, and ſealed the Truth of it with their blood. All which albeit I might here inſert in my enſuing Catalogue, as our fellow profeſſors,<note place="margin">Euſeb. li. 8. c. 1.</note> becauſe (as <hi>Euſebius</hi> noteth) they all adhered to the Doctrine of the Apoſtles; neyther were they entangled with theſe new-found Popiſh Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, neyther heard they of that yoake of ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude which the now Church of Rome layeth vpon her followers: yet I will onely content my ſelfe with a few of them, and that ſuch as in their writings and actions deteſted and abhorred thoſe things which were after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards brought in by the Popiſh Myſterie of Iniquitie: of which number in thoſe times, wee haue not a few conſenting with vs, as may appeare in this Catalogue following.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20231:50"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20231:50"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:20231:51"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:20231:51"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:20231:52"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:20231:52"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:20231:53"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:20231:53"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:20231:54"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:20231:54"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:20231:55"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:20231:55"/>
               <head>Betweene the yeares 250. and 300.</head>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>FAbian,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chanemon,</hi> of Nilus,</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fructuoſus,</hi> of Tarracona,</item>
                  </list> marryed Biſhops.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cyprian,</hi> an African, borne in Carthage, who although he had his grieuous errors, yet was a worthie Builder of the Houſe of God, not by word alone, but alſo by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. <hi>Auguſtine de Baptiſm. contra Donat. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 17. In his Writings he agreeth with vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Narciſſus,</hi> Biſhop of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, a great enemie to Superſtition, <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aſclepiades,</hi> Biſhop of Antiochia; of whom <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> Biſhop of Ieruſalem (being the priſoner of Chriſt in Caeſarea) wrote vnto the people in Antiochia, That it was a comfort vnto him, and it made his Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the more eaſie, that he heard of the zeale and conſtancie of <hi>Aſclepiades, Euſeb. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Babilas,</hi> Biſhop of Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia (vpon whom albeit the Papiſts would father many of their ſuperſtitious deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) yet <hi>Euſebius,</hi> who may bee beſt credited in this point, ſheweth his hatred of all Idolatrie; and therefore (no doubt) likewiſe of ſuch Idolatrous inuentions, <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeb. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 39.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Betweene the yeares 200. and 250.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>TErtullian</hi> (who albeit hee fell into the Error of <hi>Montanus,</hi> and held diuers other Errors) yet where he was Orthodoxe, ſtood moſt with vs, as</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Origen</hi> (of whom the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe is, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi bene nemo me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius, vbi male nemo prius</hi>) where hee writeth beſt, is for vs, as</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Polycrates,</hi> Biſhop of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch, a marryed Biſhop, together with diuers other Biſhops of Aſia, withſtood <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictor,</hi> Biſhop of Rome, and oppoſed certaine Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by him vrged, about Obſeruation of Dayes, Meats, Drinkes, Veſtures, &amp;c. <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 26.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:20231:56"/>
               <head>Betweene the yeeres 150. <hi>and</hi> 200.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>POlycarpus,</hi> Biſhop of Smyrna, who reſiſted <hi>Anicetus,</hi> Biſhop of Rome, and withſtood diuers Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, then beginning to be ſet on foot, <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 26.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Polycarpus</hi> alſo wrote an Epiſtle to the Philippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, wherein hee defendeth the ſame Doctrine of Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by Faith, as we doe, <hi>Iren. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> Biſhop of Lyons in France, who though hee was entangled with the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of the Chyliaſts, yet where he was Orthodoxe, ioyned with vs, and wrote in the name of his brethren of France vnto <hi>Victor,</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome, reproouing him for offering to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate the Churches of Aſia, who withſtood his Traditions, <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 26.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Melito,</hi> Biſhop of Sardis, wrote an Apologie for the Chriſtians to <hi>Antonius</hi> the Emperor, <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 13. His conſent together with vs, about the Canonicall Scripture, and the Apocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha, may be ſeene in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to <hi>Oneſimus, Melit. Apolog. ad Oneſim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Congregations at Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Vienna in France, how they accord with vs, may be ſeene by the Epiſtle ſet forth in their name, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat Martyrol. p.</hi> 40.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Betweene the yeeres 100. <hi>and</hi> 150.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IGnatius,</hi> who in the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of <hi>Traian</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, was for the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Faith deliuered to wilde Beaſts, to be deuoured, <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeb. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 35, 36.</p>
               <p>It is written of him, That as hee paſſed through Aſia, being vnder the moſt ſtrict cuſtodie of his Garders, hee ſtrengthened and confirmed the people euerie where, as hee went, and admoniſhed them eſpecially, and before other things, to beware and ſhun Hereſies, and vaine Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, newly riſen vp, and that they ſhould cleaue onely to the Writings of the Apoſtles, &amp;c. <hi>Ex Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom. in Catal. Sanct. Eccl.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:20231:56"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iuſtinus Martyr,</hi> who wrote two bookes of <hi>Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie</hi> for the Chriſtians to the Emperour <hi>Antoninus Pius;</hi> In the which and in his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alogues hee teſtifieth the ſumme and ſubſtance of the doctrine and Religion of the Chriſtians in thoſe times, wholy anſwering with ours now, if wee compare them together. <hi>Iuſtin. Dialog. cum Tryph. &amp; Apol.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quadratus,</hi> Biſhop of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Agrippus Caſtor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hegiſippus,</hi> and others.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Betweene the yeeres <hi>50.</hi> and <hi>100.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SAint <hi>Iohn</hi> the Euangeliſt, who for preaching the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. 3. c. 10.</note> was baniſhed by <hi>Domitian</hi> into the Ile <hi>Path<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> about the yeare 97. and after the death of the aforeſaid <hi>Domitian,</hi> was releaſed againe vnder <hi>Pertinax</hi> the Emperour, and came to <hi>Epheſus anno</hi> 100. where hee continued vntill the time of <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ian,</hi> and liued till the yeare after the paſſion of our Sauiour 99. How our doctrine doth agree with his, may be ſeene if we examine it by his Writings.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Peter. Simeon</hi> Biſhop of Hieruſalem. <hi>Iacobus Iuſtus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S. <hi>Paul, Oneſimus</hi> Biſhop of Sardis. <hi>Titus.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <head>THE CHVRCHES OF</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Corinth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Galatia.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Philippi.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Coloſſos.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Theſſalonica</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Crete.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Epheſus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pergamus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thyatyra.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sardis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Smyrna.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Philadelphia</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Laodicea.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:20231:57"/>
               <head>Betweene the firſt yeere of our Sauiors <hi>Incarnation, and the</hi> 50. <hi>after.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEſides <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, old <hi>Simeon, Hanna</hi> the daughter of <hi>Phannel,</hi> &amp;c. wee haue the Twelue Apoſtles:
<list>
                     <item>SIMON PETER.</item>
                     <item>ANDREVV.</item>
                     <item>IAMES, the ſonne of <hi>Zebedee.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>IOHN.</item>
                     <item>PHILIP.</item>
                     <item>BARTHOLOMEVV.</item>
                     <item>THOMAS.</item>
                     <item>MATTHIAS.</item>
                     <item>IAMES, the ſonne of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>LEBBEVS, whoſe ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name was <hi>Thaddeus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>SIMON, the Canaanite.</item>
                     <item>MATTHIAS, choſen in the place of <hi>Judas Iſcariot.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>IESVS CHRIST HIMSELFE BEING THE HEAD CORNER STONE.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:20231:57"/>
               <p>THat the Apoſtles taught the ſame Doctrine which wee embrace; and thoſe Churches (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned) vnto whom the Apoſtles wrote, did follow the ſame Religion which wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, may appeare, if we compare our Doctrine and Religion with theirs; which, in ſtead of many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, wee may behold in this briefe Table beneath ſpecified.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>THE DOCTRINE OF THE Apoſtles, and profeſſion of the Churches <hi>vnto whom they wrote:</hi>
                     </head>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">Agreeing with vs PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TESTANTS.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Diſagreeing from the PAPISTS.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Scripture ſufficiencie.</cell>
                        <cell>Traditions.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>IOhn 5.39. Iohn 20.31. Act. 17.10. Luk. 16.29. Eph. 2.20. 2. Tim. 3.15, 16, 17.</cell>
                        <cell>IOhn 4. 22, 23. 1. Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moth. 4.1. 2. Timoth. 3.1. Reuelat. 22.18, 19.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Scripture perſpicuitie.</cell>
                        <cell>Slander of obſcuritie.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Matth. 7.7. Rom. 10.6. 2. Cor. 4.3.</cell>
                        <cell>Rom. 15.4. 1. Theſſ. 5.20. 2. Pet. 1.19.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Scripture authoritie.</cell>
                        <cell>Authoritie of the Church.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Iohn 5.34, 36, 39. Luk. 16.19. &amp; 1. Ioh. 5 6.</cell>
                        <cell>Act. 2.42. &amp; 19, 20. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ. 5.14.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:20231:58"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Sacraments.</cell>
                        <cell>Sacraments.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Their number. <hi>Math.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.16. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.19. Their efficacie. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. The fruits and effects of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.23. The Sacrament of the Lords Supper.<note place="margin">Artic 31.</note> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.11. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.10. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.17. Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall eating and drinking in the Sacrament. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.3. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.29. Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating in both kinds. <hi>Math.</hi> 26.26. Mark. 14.22. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Their ſeauen-fold number.</hi> 1. Cor. 11.23. Reue. 22.18. <hi>Their opus operatum.</hi> Eph 4.5. <hi>Their whole taking away ſinne.</hi> Rom. 7.7, 8. 1. Ioh. 1.8. <hi>Their ſacrifice of the Maſſe.</hi> Heb. 7.24. &amp; 9.15. &amp; 10.10. <hi>Reall preſence.</hi> Ioh. 6.35. Act. 3.21. 1. Cor. 11.37. <hi>Keeping backe the cup from the lay people.</hi> 1. Cor. 11.33.34.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The true manner of Gods worſhip.</cell>
                        <cell>Will-worſhip.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Tit. 1.5. Hebr. 13.7. 1. Pet. 1.23.</cell>
                        <cell>Coloſſ. 2.18, 20, 23. Math. 15.9.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The danger of all ſinne.</cell>
                        <cell>Veniall ſinnes.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Rom. 4.15. 1. Ioh. 3.4.</cell>
                        <cell>Rom. 6.23. Iames 1.15.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Prayer.</cell>
                        <cell>Prayer.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>To God alone.</hi> Rom. 8.27. 1. Cor. 1.16. Heb. 10.19. <hi>in a known tong.</hi> 1. Cor. 14.15.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>To Saints &amp; Angels.</hi> Rom. 10.14. Col. 2.18. <hi>In an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known tongue.</hi> 1. Cor. 14.16.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:20231:58"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The Church.</cell>
                        <cell>The Church.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Jt is a congregation of the faithfull onely, &amp;c.</hi> Ioh. 10.16. &amp; 15.14. Eph. 5.23. <hi>True markes of the Church.</hi> Act. 2.4. Eph. 2.10. Act. 5.8. <hi>Chriſt alone the head of the Church.</hi> Eph. 1.22. &amp; 4.16. Act. 4.11. 1. Cor. 1.11. <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall diſcipline.</hi> 1. Cor. 5.7. 2. Theſ. 3.14. Tit. 3.10.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>A promiſcuous company.</hi> Eph. 5.25, 26. 1. Ioh. 2.19. <hi>Falſe markes.</hi> Math. 24.23. <hi>Popiſh monarchie.</hi> 2. Theſſ. 2.4, 6, 7. Reuel. 13.8. <hi>Popiſh Hierarchy, pardons, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſions.</hi> Act. 11.28. 2. Cor. 10.4.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Sanctification.</cell>
                        <cell>Sanctification.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Jn true holines and newneſſe of life.</hi> Rom. 16.4. Luk. 1.75 Eph. 1.4. Philip. 1.12. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſ. 1.22.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Jn obſeruation of dayes and meates.</hi> Coloſſ. 2.16. Rom. 14.14.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Faith.</cell>
                        <cell>Faith.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>An aſſured confidence.</hi> Mark 5.7. 2. Tim. 2.8. <hi>vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on knowledge.</hi> Heb. 11.1. 2. Cor. 13.5. <hi>only in the elect,</hi> Ioh. 6.35.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>A beliefe in generall.</hi> Rom. 10.14. <hi>Jmplicite.</hi> Iam. 2.19. <hi>in hereticks and wicked men.</hi> 2. Theſſ. 3.2.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Repentance.</cell>
                        <cell>Repentance.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>The gift of God.</hi> Geneſ. 8.21. Rom. 8.7. <hi>Neceſſarie.</hi> Iam. 1.7. 1. Tim. 2.21. <hi>Confeſſion to God.</hi> Math. 3.6.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Freewill.</hi> 1. Cor. 2.14. Coloſſ. 2.13. <hi>Meritorious.</hi> Rom. 4.5, 6. <hi>Auricular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</hi> Luk. 5.21.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:20231:59"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Good workes.</cell>
                        <cell>Good workes.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Muſt ſpring from Faith,</hi> Rom. 8.8. Galat. 5 6. Tit. 1.15. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>b 11 6. <hi>Are our dutie,</hi> Matth 7.17. 2. Pet. 1.10.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Before Iuſtification,</hi> Matth. 12.33. Luk. 6.43. Rom. 11.17. <hi>Merit of them,</hi> Rom. 5.12. Galat 3.11. Heb 11.17.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Subiection to Powers.</cell>
                        <cell>Exemption from obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Rom. 13.1, 2, 3. Tit. 3.1. 1. Pet. 2.13.</cell>
                        <cell>1. Tim. 2.1, 2. Iude 1.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Places after this life.</cell>
                        <cell>Purgatorie.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Only two, Heauen and Hell,</hi> Reuel 14.13. &amp; 22.13.</cell>
                        <cell>Luk. 23.43. 2. Cor. 12.3, 4.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>I Might inſtance in many more, yea, in all the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences betweene vs and the Papiſts, wherein I might as clearely prooue the conſent of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and thoſe Primitiue Chriſtians together with vs, and their diſſent from the Papiſts; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, prooue effectually our Church to haue beene in that ancient Primitiue Church. But theſe proofes may ſuffice, in ſtead of many; and by theſe, wee may learne what wee are to iudge of the reſt: referring the tryall of our whole Religion (in all and euerie point thereof, wherein wee differ from the Papiſts)
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:20231:59"/> vnto the touchſtone of the doctrine of our Sauiour Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and to that which in the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of ſacred Scriptures is commended vnto the Churches; which indeede is the onely true rule to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine by, and to end Controuerſies.</p>
               <p>But our Romaniſts will none of that; for they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure their Religion to come vnder this tryall of Gods word; neither will it content them that wee make triall thereby,<note place="margin">See the Fiſher caught in his owne Net.</note> which was the reaſon that <hi>Fiſher</hi> in the late conference, neither could denie that Chriſt and his Apoſtles taught the ſame faith and doctrine, which the Proteſtants now profeſſe, nor would abide the triall by it, but fled from that to the practiſe of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing times, and more remote:<note place="margin">Canus, loc. li. 3. c. 3. p. 151.</note> for <hi>Canus</hi> a Writer of their owne, confeſſeth, <hi>That the moſt points of the Roman faith are not contained in the Scripture:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Andrad. Orth. Exp. lib. 2.</note> And <hi>Andradius</hi> ſpeaketh plainely, That <hi>many points of the now Romiſh faith would reele and totter, if they were not ſupported by the helpe of Tradition.</hi> Therefore our Maſſe Prieſts will not endure the reſolution of the now depending con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies between: vs and them, ſhould be tried by the authority of the Scriptures. <hi>Take from them</hi> (ſaith <hi>Standiſh) their Engliſh damnable tranſlations,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Standiſh, ca. 6. pro. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>and let them learne to giue as much credit to that which is not expreſſed, as to that which is expreſſed in the Scripture.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Briſt. Mot. vlt.</note> And <hi>Briſto</hi> teaching his Scholler how to deale with a Proteſtant, biddeth him, <hi>Firſt get the weake and proud heretick out of his weake and falſe Caſtle of onely Scripture into the plaine field of Traditions, and then like cowards they ſhall not be able to ſtand.</hi> Alas, what ſmall founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath that Religion of theirs, which is onely ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:20231:60"/> by Traditions? what comfort can there be in that Religion, which is afraid to be tried by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?</p>
               <p>Hitherto I haue ſhewed the aſcent of the Proteſtants Church, from before <hi>Luthers</hi> dayes, euen to the time of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles, and found our Church (which the Papiſts traduce as a Nouice) euen in the primitiue Church; our Religion (which they taxe as a new Religion) to be the firſt Religion Chriſtian: I could now deriue it from an higher ſtraine, and ſhew it in a more auncient time, before Chriſt was manifeſted in the fleſh, euen in the daies of the Prophets, whoſe agreement with vs, and diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Papiſts, I might euidently conuince out of their Writings; Before them, in the time of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and vnder the Law; Before the Law, in the Patriarchs; Before them, and before the Flood, in <hi>Noah, Enoch, Abel,</hi> and ſo bring it to the very beginning, euen to the time of <hi>Adam.</hi> But this would be a needleſſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: for if we proue (as already hath beene proued) That our Church hath beene as auncient as the time of Chriſt and his Apoſtles; the other muſt needes follow, That it is as auncient as <hi>Adams</hi> time, and from the beginning:<note place="margin">Cantic. 6.9. Epheſ. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Becauſe the Church of Chriſt is but one, and there is but one Faith, one Lord, one Baptiſme.</hi> The Fathers before the Law,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.3, 4.</note> and thoſe who liued vnder the Law, though they and we differ in ſome outward Rites and Ceremonies,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.11.</note> yet for ſubſtance embrace one and the ſame Religion, haue one and the ſame Truth, one and the ſame Foundation:<note place="margin">Eph. 4.11.</note> That Church which was founded vpon the doctrine of the Prophets and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:20231:60"/> Apoſtles, Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe being the head corner ſtone, euer was from the beginning, ſhall euer be to the end of the world. Such is ours, and ſuch is our Religion: Therefore we conclude, That our Church and our Religion is no vpſtart; but the true Church of Chriſt, the ancienteſt and only Orthodox Religion.</p>
               <p>And now (O ye ſeducing Papiſts, ye Ieſuiticall Fry, and Seminarie Frogs, which are crept vp out of the mouth of the falſe Prophet, and ſculk abroad to ſeduce people) what haue you to ſay for your ſelues? with what face can you impute nouelty to vs?<note place="margin">Reu. 16.14, 15.</note> how dare ye buzze into the eares of your Proſelites, That our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion was neuer heard of vntill <hi>Luthers</hi> dayes? perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture you take your ayme at this, becauſe the name of Proteſtants came in neere about that time. The name indeede aroſe vpon occaſion of a Proteſtation made by the 14. principall Cities, and diuers Princes of Germany, at the Dyet of Noremberg,<note place="margin">Ioh. Sleid. lib. 3. Hiſt. of the Trent. Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel. lib. 1. p. 48.</note> appealing from the Pope vnto the Emperour, and to a generall Councell, in which proteſtation was contained a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of their faith, and of thoſe grieuances which they had againſt the Church of Rome; for which, by their aduerſaries, they were termed Proteſtants. Now wee although wee are not aſhamed of that name, yet ſtand not ſo much vpon the name, glorying in no name ſo much as in the name of Chriſtians. And that ſuch proteſtations were made, ſuch declarations of the ſame Faith which wee profeſſe, by the Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians, Waldenſes, &amp;c. alreadie hath beene made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt. But how long time is it, I pray, that the name Papiſt (whereof of late they were aſhamed,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:20231:61"/> and wherein they now ſo much glory) was knowne or acknowledged in the world?<note place="margin">Act. 11.26. Optat. Mile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. lib 2. cont. Parm.</note> or whence is it that (leauing the auncient name of Chriſtians) they ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (with the Donatiſts) appropriate vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the name of Catholicks?</p>
               <p>Doubtleſſe, howſoeuer they bragge and boaſt of Antiquity, wee may apply that of <hi>Bildad</hi> vnto them, <hi>They are but of yeſterday:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 8.9.</note> for how could a man know what it was to be a Papiſt;<note place="margin">Trent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel concluded, An. dom. 1563.</note> or what was the body of Religion before the Councell of Trent had defined it, which was ſince <hi>Luthers</hi> time? Let them ſhew where their Papall Supremacie was, before the time of Pope <hi>Goodface</hi> the third:<note place="margin">Platina.</note> or their Latine Seruice, before the yere 680.<note place="margin">Iacob. de Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag. in vit. Gregor. Expoſit. Rom. ord. ann. 1215, 1222. ex Act. Rom. Pontif. 1414.</note> or their Romiſh Maſſe, before <hi>Adrian</hi> the 1. <hi>Anno</hi> 780. or their <hi>Agnus Dei,</hi> before Pope <hi>Sergius, an.</hi> 700. or their Tranſubſtantiation, before the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Lateran: or their eleuation and adoration of the Sacrament, before the time of <hi>Honorius</hi> the third: or their receiuing of the Communion in one kinde onely, and the abſolute forbidding of the contrary, before the Councell of <hi>Conſtance:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohan. Scot. lib. 4. diſt. 17. artic. 3. Idem, ibid.</note> or their abſolute neceſſity of Auricular Confeſſion, before <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, in his Councell of Lateran: or the prohibition of Marriage to the Clergie, before the ſame time? I might inſtance in many other points of Poperie, which howſoeuer they may carrie ſome ſhew and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of Antiquity; yet being duly conſidered, they will appeare to be but late inuentions, peeced and patched together by their Popes, as each of them in their ſucceſſion was minded to adde ſomething, to make vp the full meaſure of the myſterie of Iniquity.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:20231:61"/>
               <p>Neyther let them boaſt (as of commonly they cracke) of the ancient Church of Rome,<note place="margin">Rhem. annot. in Act. 11. ſec. 4. Idem, in Eph. 4.13.</note> ſo famouſly renowned by the Writings of the Apoſtles, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended and appealed vnto by the auncient Fathers: for the name and ſhew of the Romane Church,<note place="margin">See M. Fox his deſcription of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the now Church of Rome, and the old. Acts and Monum. firſt 26. pages.</note> is but an emptie ſhew of Names, and Titles; this preſent Romane being in a manner wholly departed, in the Queſtions controuerted, from the auncient, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth nothing but the Title. The true, auncient, and Apoſtolike Church of Rome, ſo much commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Fathers, and ſought to by the World, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed another kind of Faith then this doth, and the ſame that we now defend againſt them: That Church affected no ſuch prowd and ſwelling Titles, it vſurped no ſuch tranſcendent Iuriſdictions, it obſerued no ſuch fooliſh Superſtitions, it maintained contrarie Doctrine to their now Errors. To what purpoſe then ſhould any ſticke vpon the name of the Romane Church, when the true Faith is changed? Or what doe the Prerogatiues and Royalties of the auncient Church concerne this, that is turned to another Religion? Or who regardeth an Houſe of ſtately Building, or anticke memorie of auncient Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, when the Plague hath infected it, and Theeues poſſeſſe it?</p>
               <p>Leaue therefore, yee Romaniſts, to cracke of your Antiquitie, or to traduce vs of Noueltie; wee may take vp the words of <hi>Nicephorus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Concil. Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin. pag. 307.</note> the Patriarke of Conſtantinople, in an Epiſtle to <hi>Leo,</hi> Biſhop of Rome: <hi>Wee alſo haue the Name of Rome</hi> (the true and auncient Faith of Rome) <hi>among vs, being built vpon one and the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:20231:62"/> ſame foundation of Faith; in matter of Faith we follow them: Wherefore let S.</hi> Paul <hi>glorie and reioice in vs alſo, and ioyning new things with old, and comparing vs in Doctrines, and Preaching, let him glorie in vs both alike; for wee as well as they, following the Doctrines and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions wherein wee are rooted, are confirmed in the confeſsion of our Faith, wherein wee ſtand, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for you (my poore ſeduced Countreymen) who ſuffer your ſelues to be ſeduced and mis-led by theſe Popiſh Circumcellions, take heed and beware how you fauour theſe Merchants of the Romiſh Strumpet, who vnder fained pretences and ſubtile in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuations goe about to make merchandiſe of your ſoules:<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Theſe latter dayes</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>are peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous times,</hi> and theſe Popiſh Prieſts and Ieſuits (I may ſay) are perillous ſeducers:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Tim. 3.1, 6, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>They of this ſort creepe into houſes, and lead captiue ſilly women, laden with ſinnes, and led about with diuers Luſts, euer learning, and neuer able to come to the knowledge of the Truth.</hi> Liſten not vnto them: It is not good for <hi>Eue</hi> to fall to conference with the Serpent;<note place="margin">Geneſ. 3.</note> no, nor for <hi>Adam</hi> neyther to ſuffer <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> and the Serpents parley, or to encline vnto them, leaſt hee alſo be partaker in the Tranſgreſſion. Conſider what is the end they ayme at: not Religion, but the Soueraigntie of their high-towring Church; not the Conſciences of men, yeelding to their Ceremonies and Superſtitions, will ſatisfie them, vnleſſe they haue their wills in ouer-ruling all, and bringing them vnder their Antichriſtian Yoake. How doe they diſturbe Thrones, and fill the World with Anarchie and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions?
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:20231:62"/> and whoſe ſoules they ſhould winne to God, by miniſtring the Word and Sacraments, their bloud they ſacrifice to the Deuill, by ſtirring them vp to Treaſon and Rebellion. <hi>Beloued,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>beleeue not euery Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, but trie the Spirits whether they be of God, or no A Foole</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon) beleeueth euery thing.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou.</note> And ſurely it is their folly, who ſuffer themſelues to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, by giuing too eaſie credit to the ſlauering inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuations of theſe Popiſh Teachers, and are hereby brought into a great diſlike of our Church, becauſe they beleeue their words, and doe not make ſearch and enquirie after the truth of the ſame. Beware leaſt that dreadfull iudgement of God fall vpon you,<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2, 10, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they receiued not the knowledge of the Truth, that they might be ſaued, therefore God ſhall ſend them ſtrong deluſions, that they ſhould beleeue lyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You will ſay, That you are no Changelings, That yee are of the olde Religion, That you keepe the olde Faith, and will liue and dye in the ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion which your fore-fathers profeſſed. Poore ſoules; Popiſh Religion is not the oldeſt Religion, but a late vpſtart, a Modell of Superſtition: your Popes Catholike Church is but an Impoſtume, growne in the Church. Wee confeſſe, that for a long time, the Chriſtian World hath beene annoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it; yet euen in the time, and before the time of this declining from the Truth, our Faith and Religion hath euer kept it ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted. The true cauſe, why during the former ouer-clouding times of Poperie, the Exerciſes of our Religion haue beene neyther ſo frequent,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:20231:63"/> nor ſo publike as now it is, eyther in place or perſons, was the perſecution of Poperie, and the generall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of the Papacie, which as a Leproſie infected, and as a Myſt obſcured the Times; ſo that ſometimes not the true beleeuers themſelues (ſuch I meane as are come to our knowledge) were void of error in euery point, though they firmely held the foundation. And if it pleaſed God in proceſſe of time to giue more libertie to the perſons, and more puritie to the Doctrine, why are wee vnthankfull? and why ſhould any enuie, if the Truth hath growne more ripe in our Age?</p>
               <p>And if there be any yet among vs (I would to God there were not too many ſuch) who ſtand as New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and lookers on, not regarding any Religion, nor caring to ioyne themſelues to either ſide, vntill they ſee the ſequell and iſſue, whether the Proteſtant or Popiſh Church is likelieſt to be moſt praeualent: To ſuch I ſay (as <hi>Elias</hi> ſaid to the people of Iſrael:) <hi>How long halt yee betweene two opinions?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. King. 18.21.</note> 
                  <hi>If the Lord be God, follow him: But if Baall, then follow him.</hi> Let them conſider and call to minde whither of the two Religions ſauour more of grace and of the ſpirit of God, whether doth attribute moſt to God, whether hath beene moſt fauoured by God: Let them conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the damnable poſitions, the horrible combuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and helliſh proiects of Poperie, and the ſauing counſels, peaceable proſperity, and heauenly bleſſings which haue accompanied ours; let them (as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle counſelleth) <hi>proue all things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 5.21.</note> 
                  <hi>and hold faſt what is good.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:20231:63"/>
               <p>If they doubt whether of them carrieth greateſt ſhew of either veritie or Antiquitie, I ſay vnto them, as it was ſaid to <hi>St. Auguſtine</hi> at the time of his conuerſion, <hi>Tolle, lege, Take vp this booke and reade:</hi> or rather as the Lord ſpeaketh by his Prophet <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, ſtand in the waies and ſee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ierem. 6.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Aske for the old paths where is the good way, and walke therein, and yee ſhall finde reſt for your ſoules.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, to the true members and vnſeduced Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of our Church, I ſay with the Apoſtle to the Corinthians, <hi>Brethren you ſee your calling,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.26.27, 28.</note> 
                  <hi>albeit not many wiſe men after the fleſh, not many mighty, not many noble are called, But God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world, to confound the wiſe; and weake things to confound the mightie, &amp;c.</hi> yet ſome noble, ſome learned, ſome Worthies, haue embraced the ſame Religion together with vs, and that in all ages and times of the world. What would wee haue? what can wee deſire more? we haue Verity and Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for vs; we haue the Patriarkes, the Prophets and Apoſtles on our ſide; we haue the company of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable Martyres, who haue ſcaled the Truth thereof with their blood: we haue the fellowſhip of many Churches in diuers Nations, Being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Compaſſed about with ſo great a clouds of Waneſſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12.1.</note> let vs follow the footſteps of thoſe who haue walked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs in this way of righteouſneſſe, and runne with patience the race that is ſet before vs. What though Papiſts raue, and rage, and plot; and ſeeke by all meanes to bring our Religion into diſgrace, yea, <hi>If it were poſsible, to cut of the name of Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 83.4.</note> 
                  <hi>that it might be no more in remembrance;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 82.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Yet theſe aduerſaries
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:20231:64" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the Lord ſhall be found lyers, but the true Church of God ſhall endure for euer.</hi> Conſider what great things God hath done for vs, and how mightily alwaies he hath defended and approued our Religion; how miraculouſly did he preſerue it, manger all the furie of the Lyon, and the wilde Boare, of the Deuill and Antichriſt, euen in the time of their greateſt perſecutions: how wonderfully hath he from time to time detected and defeated all plots and proiects, conſpiracies and trecheries of the enemies? what ſtrange deliuerances hath he giuen vnto vs? <hi>By this wee may know that God fauoureth vs becauſe our enemies preuaile not againſt vs.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.11. Pſal. 46.11.</note> 
                  <hi>The God of Iacob is with vs, the God of Hoaſts is our refuge;</hi> he hath giuen vnto vs a <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> a man after his owne heart to rule ouer vs, a <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſophat,</hi> whoſe heart is ſet to ſeeke the Lord, a <hi>Ioſias</hi> whoſe chiefeſt ſtudie is to build vp Gods houſe, and whoſe chiefeſt Title is to be the <hi>Defender of the Faith;</hi> he hath taken away our feares, by the happie returne of our moſt hopefull Prince, &amp; redoubled our ioyes in his forward zeale for the furthering of true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; he hath bleſſed vs with an Honourable aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie of States in the high Court of Parliament, and vnited their hearts and mindes to ſeeke the promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his glory, and the publike welfare of the Common-weale; he hath ſtirred vp the hearts of all faithfull Subiects within this Iland to pray, and cry <hi>Grace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zech. 4.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Grace,</hi> to that Parliamentarie aſſembly. What now remaineth, but that (as the Apoſtle counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth) <hi>Wee ſtand faſt in that libertie wherewith Chriſt hath made vs free:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 5.1.</note> and (as our Sauiour doth admoniſh vs) <hi>that wee be faithfull to the death,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note> conſtantly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:20231:64"/> and religiouſly perſeuering in that Religion which we haue learned out of the Scriptures, and which hath beene practiſed ſo long agone, in all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, by ſo many Patriarkes, Prophets, Apoſtles, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Confeſſors and holy Martyrs; That ſo wee may glorifie God, and ſtop the mouth of the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, and both by life and doctrine confound Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, <hi>till that miſterie of Iniquitie bee fully reuealed, whom the Lord ſhall conſume with the ſpirit of his mouth, and deſtroy with the brightneſſe of his comming;</hi> which we beſeech the Lord to haſten. <hi>Euen ſo Come Lord Ieſus, come quickly. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FJNIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
